<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Practical meditations upon the four last things viz. I. Death, II. Judgment, III. Hell, IV. Heaven / by R. Sherlock ...</title>
            <author>Sherlock, R. (Richard), 1612-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12198760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12198760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59770)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 898:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Practical meditations upon the four last things viz. I. Death, II. Judgment, III. Hell, IV. Heaven / by R. Sherlock ...</title>
                  <author>Sherlock, R. (Richard), 1612-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 124, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for L. Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional exercises.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56040:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56040:1"/>
            <p>PRACTICAL MEDITATIONS UPON THE Four Laſt Things: <hi>VIZ.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Death,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Iudgment,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Hell,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>Heaven.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. SHERLOCK,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEUT. XXXII. 29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood this; that they would conſider their lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.H.</hi> for <hi>L. Meredith</hi> at the <hi>Star,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="four last things" type="meditations">
            <pb facs="tcp:56040:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56040:2"/>
            <head>PRACTICAL MEDITATIONS UPON THE <hi>Four Laſt Things,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>The Firſt Meditation.</head>
               <p>THE clean Beaſt which was only commanded to be offered in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto God under the Law, was <hi>ſuch as chewed the Cud,
<note place="margin">Lev. 11.3</note> and divided the Hoof,</hi> myſtically repreſenting the qualifications of the clean and pure Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1 1 Pet. 2.4, 5.</note> who is himſelf that ſpiritual Sacrifice God requireth under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>By <hi>chewing the Cud,</hi> holy and divine Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation is intimated: by <hi>dividing the Hoof,</hi> may be myſtically meant <hi>the laſt end of man;</hi> which is a dividing aſunder the Soul from the Body by <hi>Death,</hi> and a ſeparation of the holy from the wicked by <hi>Judgment;</hi> which ſhall aſſign to either their everlaſting habitations either in <hi>Heaven</hi> or in <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56040:3"/>
               <p>Of theſe Four Laſt Things S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, that Firſt, <hi>Death</hi> is of all things to fleſh and bloud moſt formidable.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Judgment,</hi> than the which there is nothing more terrible and dreadful.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Hell,</hi> the Torments whereof are inſupportable.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Heaven,</hi> the Joys whereof are beyond Apprehenſion moſt Bliſsful and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing.</p>
               <p>And theſe Subjects of holy Meditation would prove the moſt prevalent to turn all perſons profeſſing Chriſtianity, from all the errors of their ways, whether in Opinion or Converſation, would they but ſeriouſly conſider the ſhortneſs and uncertainty of this preſent life: the ſtrict account muſt be given of all our Thoughts, Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even to every idle Word, eſpecially ſpoken to the detriment of any: That in all theſe we ſhall have the Devil and his Angels vehemently to accuſe us, and our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to teſtifie againſt us: A moſt ſevere Judge to paſs ſentence upon us: from whoſe impartial doom, the endleſs Torments of Hell ſhall receive the wilfully erroneous, and impenitent ſinner; but eternal Joys, and never fading Felicities ſhall crown the Orthodox and Holy.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56040:3"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.17.</note>
                  <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the people that forget God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſd. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>But the Souls of the righteous are in the hand of God, and there ſhall no torment touch them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ath. cr. Mat. 25. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>They that have done good, ſhall go into everlaſting life: and they that have done evil, into everlaſting fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> This Faith is profeſſed by many, but by few believed with the heart: for he that cordially believes theſe principles of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, will <hi>ſtand in awe, and ſin not:</hi> he will not dare in defiance of this Faith, knowingly and wittingly to tranſgreſs the Laws of the great Majeſty of Heaven: and 'tis ſuch a Faith attended by Fear, and this Fear by Care and Caution, that muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Soul from the Torments, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title her to the Joys of the other World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, That he who believes not, can neither Hope nor Fear: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, he who doth truly believe theſe Eſſentials of his Religion, cannot but both hope for the Happineſs, and fear the Miſery of the World to come.</p>
               <p>'Tis recorded of a Friar, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to his Abbot, that he was weary of that idle, lazy life; and therefore he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red leave to depart to ſome other place: To whom the Abbot returned anſwer, Thy lazineſs is a manifeſt ſign, that thou didſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver truly believe, and ſeriouſly conſider of the Pains of Hell, and the Joys of Heaven; for the deep ſenſe of theſe would preſerve
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56040:4"/>thee from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll lazineſs in thy Cell. <hi>Pra. Spir. cap.</hi> 142.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O that they were wiſe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.29.</note> that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the greateſt and moſt comprehenſive of all the parts of true wiſdom, ſo to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as rightly to prepare for our latter end: for to end well is the ſumm of all our hopes, and of all the happineſs we can hope for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a great vanity to deſire a long life, without the thought of leading a holy life. 'Tis a great vanity to be ſo wholly intent upon this preſent life, as not to provide for the life to come. 'Tis a great vanity to be in love with what ſuddenly fadeth away, and not to haſten in our deſires and endeavours to that joy which ſhall never end.</hi> T. K. l. 1. c. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Have mercy upon me,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.13.</note> O God, and conſider the trouble I ſuffer of them that hate me,</hi> my Spirit is troubled for the daily incurſions of my ghoſtly enemies: <hi>Thou that lifteſt me up from the Gates of Death:</hi> Such is this frail mortal life, all the ways whereof are vanity and iniquity, even Gates leading to Death eternal: From the which I humbly beg to be raiſed up, and exalted by thy right hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That I may ſhew all thy praiſes within the ports of the daughter of Sion:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> glorifie thee with thy Church Triumphant in Heaven: <hi>I will rejoyce in thy Salvation:</hi> to be thus lifted up and ſav'd, is a joy unſpeakable and glorious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember me,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.4.</note> O Lord, according to the favour thou beareſt unto thy people, and viſit me with thy Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56040:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That I may ſee the felicity of thy choſen,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and rejoyce in the gladneſs of thy people: and give thanks with thine inheritance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. II. <hi>Of the Shortneſs and Frailty of this preſent Life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAN that is born of a woman is of few days, and full of trouble.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 14.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He cometh forth like a Flower, and is cut down: he fleeth as a ſhadow,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and continueth not — In the midſt of life we be in death,</hi> whilſt every day we live is one day nearer to the end of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For what is your life?
<note place="margin">Jam. 4.14.</note> 'tis even a vapour that appeareth for a little time, and then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The time of my life paſt is already ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by death, which ſtill dogs me at the heels to devour the ſhort remainder of my flitting days.</p>
               <p>Not to conſider this ſhortneſs and frailty of humane life, is to make my life yet more ſhort and frail. So <hi>Drex. vita brevis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus</hi>— Life is ſhort unto all, but ſhorteſt unto thoſe, who forget what is paſt, are negligent in what is preſent, and fear not what is to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, make me to know mine end, and the number of my days, that I may be certified how long I have to live:</hi> that the length of my days is of the ſhorteſt meaſure: <hi>for behold thou haſte made my days as a ſpan—Verily every man living is altogether vanity:</hi> The moſt high and mighty, the moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56040:5"/>and wealthy are not exempt from this character: for Honours, Riches, Friends, all the delights of the Sons of men, with all the Pomp and Pleaſure, and power of the world, depending upon the ſhortneſs and frailty of humane Life;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nihil eſt magnum re, quod parvum tempore: nec longis dilatatur gaudiis, quicquid arcto fine concluditur.</hi> Hucher. Ep. Paran.</note> renders every man in all that he is, in all that he has, and in all that he hopes for, in this world, a vanity of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, an univerſal vanity.</p>
               <p>The divine <hi>à Kempis</hi> gives us both the reaſon and the uſe of this doctrine: <hi>Quia per peccatum</hi> — Since by Sin we have loſt our innocence, we ought with patience to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the mercy of God, until this iniquity do paſs away, and mortality be ſwallowed up of life. <hi>T. K. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div n="St Augustine" type="quotation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>S.</hi> Auguſtine<hi>'s Meditation on this Subject.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">
                              <p>THE time of my Pilgrimage here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth is tedious, weariſome — for this is a miſerable life, a frail life, an uncertain life, a bitter life, a laborious life, a ſinful life: 'tis the miſtreſs of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and ſinfulneſs, and the hand-maid to death and hell—</p>
                              <p>This life is rather to be called death than life, as being through the whole courſe thereof, a paſſing from Life to Death: for whilſt we paſs from Infancy to Childhood, from thence to Manhood, and ſo to Old-age, every ſuch change in Life is but a paſſage to death, or rather ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56040:5"/>many ſtages of Death; for each condition of life is the death of its foregoing ſtate and condition.</p>
                              <p>There is no condition in this life cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſetled; now we are glad, and anon ſad; now we are well, and anon ſick; now we are at eaſe, and anon in pain; now we laugh, and anon weep; now in hunger and thirſt, anon in fulneſs and exceſs: in honour and diſhonour, in wealth and poverty, in heats and colds, in evil report and good report, in fear and terror, and much amazement: and all this and much more than can be expreſt, is too often attended by a ſudden, unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected death; and which is yet more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, though there be nothing more certain than death, yet vain fooliſh man knoweth not, conſidereth not his end.</p>
                           </q>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.12.</note> So the Preacher: <hi>For man alſo knoweth not his time, as the fiſhes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the ſnare, ſo are the ſons of men ſnared in an evil time when it falleth ſuddenly upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> being ask'd, what is man? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Imbecillitatis exemplum; Temporis. ſpolium; fortunae luſus; inconſtantiae imago; invidiae &amp; calamitatis trutina; reliquum vero. pituita &amp; bilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid homo</hi> (inquit Gran.) <hi>cujus conceptio, culpa, naſci poena, vivere miſeria, &amp; mori, tormentum?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Silenus</hi> being ask'd by <hi>Midas: Quid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini optimum?</hi> anſwer'd: <hi>Primò, non naſci: ſccundò, quam ocyſſime mori.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56040:6"/>
               <p>O ſenſeleſs mortals! eſpecially being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, and yet to be of ſo little Faith, as to doat upon a life ſo frail, ſhort and uncertain, ſo changeable and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, in defiance of what we daily profeſs to believe, <hi>Life Everlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed are they, and they are but a few, who in hopes and deſires to enjoy the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable bleſſings of the life to come, do ſlight and deſpiſe the fallacious flattering injoyments of this world, leſt being decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the charms and fawnings thereof, the Deceiver and the Deceived periſh toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>'Tis a general complaint, that the world is deceitful, and unſatisfying in all her moſt alluring enjoyments; and yet ſo mightily the fleſh prevaileth againſt the ſpirit, that moſt men love, (and I am a great fool among the reſt) yea doatingly love to be thus deceived: too paſſionately deſiring to injoy ſtill this mortal life how frail ſoever, and attended with a numerous train of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries.</p>
               <p>But forget not, O remember and forget not, that thou art immortal (O my ſoul) and that death is but the change of a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for a quiet life, of a frail for a fixed and permanent Being; of an uncertain for a certain abode, and of a temporary for life everlaſting. 'Tis but the falling in pieces of an earthly Tabernacle, and <hi>when it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> thou haſt a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis a fam'd ſaying of <hi>Benedict: Malus mortem, bonus vitam formidat:</hi> In the death
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56040:6"/>of the righteous is his hopes of happineſs, but in the continuance of this life doth the wicked truſt.</p>
               <p>Thou wouldſt not fear the end of this life, didſt thou rightly hope for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a better: 'Tis for want of treaſures laid up in Heaven, the fruits of true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that thou art afraid to die, and 'twill be too late to labour for them, when death approacheth.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O <hi>Almighty God, who alone canſt order the unruly wills and affections of ſinful men, grant unto thy people (and to me with them) to love the thing which thou comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and deſire that which thou doſt promiſe; that ſo among the ſundry and manifold chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the world, our hearts may ſurely there be fixed where true joys are to be found, through</hi> Jeſus <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. III. <hi>Of the frequent Remembrance of Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THIS preſent Life is the School of Death, wherein we are taught the ſeveral leſſons of living to die well, or ſo to die, that we may live Eternally.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Climacus ſcal. grad.</hi> 6. records a ſtory of a Brother, who had lived negligently for many years, and was at laſt ſurprized with ſuch a deſperate diſeaſe, that he was for ſo long a time depriv'd of his Senſes, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56040:7"/>he was ſuppoſed to be abſolutely dead: but recovering again, he immediately ſecluded himſelf from all ſociety, and continued for Twelve years, which was the remainder of his time, in that ſolitary ſeparate conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, lamenting continually the negligences and ſins of his by-paſt life, and the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all ſuch perſons who die in their ſins unrepented.</p>
               <p>And when the time of his death indeed approached, many of his fraternity flock'd to him, deſiring to hear ſome more than ordinary inſtructions, and directions from him for the good of their Souls: but all that he would ſay was this, as the ſumm of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian wiſdom: <hi>If you deſire ſo to live that ye may die happily, then meditate continually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on death: for 'tis ſcarce poſſible for that man to ſin, who with due regard remembers Death, the wages of Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid by the ſaid <hi>Climacus,</hi> That <hi>the meditation of death is as neceſſary to preſerve the health of the Soul in the life of grace, as is daily bread to preſerve the body in the life of nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The forgetfulneſs of Death is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of all the Sins of the ſons of men: hence the neglect of all the duties we owe to God and Man: hence the abuſe of all the bleſſings of God, whether relating to this or the other world: hence all luxury, and all the ſinful pleaſures of the fleſh: hence all covetouſneſs, and carnal cares for the things of this life: hence all forgetfulneſs of the great account we muſt make of all the works done in the body, together with the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56040:7"/>from our minds of all fears of Hell, and hopes of Heaven: 'Tis therefore good advice the wiſe <hi>Syracides</hi> gives us;
<note place="margin">Ecclus. 28.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy end, and let enmity ceaſe: Remember corruption and death, and abide in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould not ſurely dare to ſin againſt my God, would I but ſeriouſly conſider in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act I do, and in every moment I breath, I am haſtening to my laſt breath, and that then I muſt give account as of every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my time, ſo of every work, both good and evil, at what time ſoever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. And 'twas ſurely thus S. <hi>Paul died daily.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.31.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To die the death of the righteous is the deſire even of the wicked;
<note place="margin">Numb. 23.10.</note> but his laſt end ſhall be very unlike the others.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t tibi mors foelix contingat, vivere diſce:</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t foelix poſſis vivere, diſce mori.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The only way to die well, is to live well; and he that will live well, muſt live by dying principles: ſaying with holy <hi>David, My Soul is continually in my hand:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.109.</note> and for ought I know it may expire at my next breathing, ſince many thouſands in this very moment do breath their laſt.</p>
               <p>And 'tis only this moment I can call mine: for what time of my life is paſt, cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again to be enjoyed, and what's to come is not in mine,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.17. Acts 17.28.</note> but in the Lord's power: <hi>My time is in thy hand. In him we live and move, and have our being.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56040:8"/>
               <p>Quam foelix &amp; prudens—<hi>He is both a wiſe, and a happy man, whoſe endeavours are, ſo to be qualified in his life, as he deſires to be found in his death.</hi> T.K. In order here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, 'tis the wholſome advice of a Father, <hi>Cum mane fuerit</hi>— when 'tis morning, think that perhaps thou mayſt not ſee the evening; and when evening comes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that 'tis uncertain whether thou ſhalt ſee morning.</p>
               <p>Thoſe <hi>Indian</hi> wiſemen call'd <hi>Brachmans,</hi> had their Sepulchres before their doors: that both upon their going out, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, they might remember their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching death, as a curb to reſtrain them from all extravagant luſtings after the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, riches and honours of this mortal life.</p>
               <p>'Tis recorded of <hi>John</hi> the famous Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that whilſt he was in perfect health he had his monument fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but not finiſhed: and that he gave order upon every Feſtival after the publick offices of the Church were ended, one of the Prieſts ſhould ſay unto him aloud; Holy Father, your Monument ſhould be finiſhed,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.43.</note> becauſe <hi>'tis not known at what hour the thief cometh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot better adviſe both my ſelf and my Reader, than that in every thing we go about we would every man of us ask himſelf this queſtion: <hi>Would I now do this if I were ready to die?</hi> 'Tis the Wiſeman's advice, <hi>whatſoever thou takeſt in hand, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the end,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7. ult.</note> and thou ſhalt never do amiſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56040:8"/>
               <p>When an Emperor of the Eaſt was new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaimed, before he ſpake to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the ſtile of Majeſty, a Maſon comes to him, and ſhewing him ſeveral kinds of Marble, demands of which of thoſe kinds of ſtone he would have his Sepulchre made: intimating unto him, that although he was made an Emperor, he was not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get he was a mortal; and therefore it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned him, with ſuch juſtice and mercy to govern his Earthly Kingdom, that he might not forfeit the loſs of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From the forgetfulneſs of my death, and the uncertainty of my life, from every evil work whereunto ſuch forgetfulneſs may betray me, and from a ſudden, and an unprepared death,</hi> good Lord deliver me.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord cloathed our firſt Parents with the skins of Beaſts, to put them in mind of that mortality and corruption of the fleſh they had contracted by their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his commands: the which as we their ſinful off-ſpring do daily bear about us, ſo ought we alſo to have the ſame in a continual remembrance for the keeping under the unruly luſts of the fleſh, that we finally paſs not from a ſpiritual to death eternal.</p>
               <p>And thus, every truly pious man thus remembers daily the unavoidable death of his corruptible body, ſo as to keep his Soul unſpotted of the world, and alive from the death of ſin, <hi>continually mortifying all his evil and corrupt affections, and daily proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all vertue and godlineſs of living.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56040:9"/>
               <p>And thus in the ſence of the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of our Lord, <hi>To die daily,</hi> is not only daily to remember death, but daily to die unto ſin, and live unto righteouſneſs unto the hopes of Eternal happineſs: ſlighting all the falſe and flattering felicities of this fawning world, as being not only empty and unſatisfying, but alſo mortal and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>A holy confidence to die well, and in hopes to enjoy Life Eternal after Death, is begotten in the heart, (ſaith the ſpiritual <hi>A Kempis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A <hi>Kempis</hi> de Imit. Chriſt. l. 1. c. 23.</note>) 1. <hi>By a perpetual contempt of the world.</hi> 2. <hi>By a thorough ſelf-denial.</hi> 3. <hi>By a fervent deſire and endeavour for proficiency in Grace.</hi> 4. <hi>By the love of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, or ſtrict corporeal Auſterities.</hi> 5. <hi>By the unwearied labour of true Repentance.</hi> 6. <hi>By a willing and ready obedience to all God's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> 7. <hi>By ſuffering contentedly; yea, even joyfully all adverſities for the love of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus prepare for thy change to come, looking not (as becomes an Immortal Soul) <hi>at the things which are ſeen,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.28.</note> but at the things which are not ſeen: for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O God the protector of all that truſt in thee, without whom nothing is ſtrong, nothing is holy: Increaſe and multiply up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us thy mercy; that thou being our leader and guide, we may ſo paſs through things temporal, that we finally loſe not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56040:9"/>the things eternal: Grant this, O heavenly Father, for thy Son <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. IV. <hi>Of the Horror of Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. UNder the Law, when a Fowl was to be offered for a burnt Sacrifice unto the Lord, The head was to be wrung off;
<note place="margin">Levit. 1.16.</note> the crop with the feathers to be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place of aſhes: Intimating myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally that the way to mortifie the ſwellings of pride and luxury, and make all the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of ſecular pomp and vanity to flag, is to turn our eyes unto the aſhes of the dead, and ſee the horrid ſtate of ſuch as lye in the Grave, even of the moſt high, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and pompous that ever liv'd upon earth.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>"S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being with his Mother <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</hi> invited to <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Pontianus</hi> the Prefect, to view the ſtately Edifices, and ancient Monuments of that eminent Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, amongſt other rareties, he ſaw the great <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Sepulchre, and therein his carcaſs of a livid, gaſtly colour; his face faln away to ſuch a meagre leanneſs, as ſcarce of skin and bone conſiſting; his Lips being rotted away, his Teeth were ſeen black and corrupted; his Noſe ſo conſumed, that only the wide hollows of his Noſtrils appeared; his Belly burſt, and ſwarming with Worms and Serpents; his Eyes quite ſunk into his head, and in the two holes thereof two loathſome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56040:10"/>Toads were feeding— Then turning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Mother, he ſaid: What now, dear Mother, is become of the great <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> whoſe pomp, and power, and policy; whoſe riches, honour and dignity; whoſe many victories, conqueſts and triumphs rendred him the moſt admired Heroe the world afforded? Where now is all his glory? Where the Conquering Armies he commanded? The Cities, Nations, Countries he ſubdued? The numerous train of Nobility, Gentry, Souldiery that attended him? The vaſt riches and boundleſs authority he acquired?—</p>
                  <p>Whereunto the pious Matron anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, O my Son! no ſooner did his Spirit fail, and his breath expire, but all his ſplendid enjoyments, all his flattering worldly felicities forſook him: His riches, his friends, his attendants, all his conqueſts and triumphs, all the honour which he got through manifold travels, pains and perils, have all now left him alone in this gaſtly ſilent Sepulchre, accompanied only with Worms, Stench and Corruption.—</p>
               </q>
               <p>Such is the end of all fleſh: <hi>All fleſh is graſs,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.6.</note> and all the goodlineſs thereof as a flower of the field.</hi> The flower is more gay and gawdy than the graſs for a little ſpace, but when the verdure of both decays, they have the ſame withered complexion, they rot and corrupt both alike; and commonly the more gawdy flower is more ugly and ſtinking than the graſs: 'Tis even ſo with the rich, and the poor, the honourable and the baſe in this world, they differ only in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56040:10"/>their outward faſhion and appearance: but when death doth ſeize them they are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obnoxious to the ſame ſolitude, poverty, and nakedneſs, to the ſame ſtench, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and rottenneſs.</p>
               <p>'Tis as true of the greateſt Prince, as of the meaneſt Peaſant: <hi>When a man is dead,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.11.</note> he ſhall inherit creeping things, Beaſts and Worms.</hi> All the difference in the Grave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the rich and the poor, is this; That the duſt of the rich, through the luxury, laſciviouſneſs, and intemperance of their life, is more corrupt and loathſome after their death, than is the duſt of the poor, whoſe food and nouriſhment was more courſe and ſparing.</p>
               <p>Why then, my Immortal Soul, art thou ſo fond of thy corruptible companion, the Body? Remember, its beginning is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and its end rottenneſs? 'Tis thy ſervant for the preſent, but if thou too much cocker and pamper it, 'twill rebel, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due, and lead thee captive to a worſe death, than that whereunto it ſelf is liable, even the death of the nether Hell;
<note place="margin">Mar. 9.44.</note> 
                  <hi>Where the Worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Death is the wages of ſin:</hi> And I have ſinned, vile wretch that I am, I have ſinned, and <hi>what ſhall I do,</hi> or <hi>what ſhall I ſay unto thee, O thou preſerver of man?</hi> All that I can ſay is the ſame ſtill;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.18.</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> and as long as I have a day to live I will ſay it: <hi>I will confeſs my wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and be ſorry for my ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mercy, good Lord, mercy I humbly beg:
<note place="margin">Job 7.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>O why doſt thou not pardon my Tranſgreſſion, and take away mine iniquity?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56040:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not my days few, ceaſe then, and let me alone, that I may bewail my ſins, and take comfort a little,</hi> in the hopes of the pardon of them, through faith in the blood of my dear Redeemer,
<note place="margin">Job 10.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>before I go to the place from whence I ſhall not return, to the land of darkneſs, and of the ſhadow of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. I know that to fleſh and blood death is of all terribles the moſt terrible, <hi>Job</hi> 18.14. but my bleſſed Redeemer hath pulled out the ſting, and quelled the terrors of death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> 56, 57. He hath alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him that had the power of death, that is, the Devil. So that now when death approacheth, through Faith and a good Conſcience I ſhall have hope, with all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and contentment, to drink off that Cup, how bitter and painful ſoever, ſaying with my bleſſed Lord and Maſter upon his approaching death,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Father, not my will, but thine be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>ASſiſt me mercifully, O Lord, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject my rebellious fleſh to the guidance of the Spirit, and my ſpirit to the Laws of my Redeemer, that when my body ſhall be the inheritance of Worms and creeping things, my Soul may poſſeſs <hi>an inheritance uncorruptible, and undefiled, that fadeth not away, reſerved in the Heavens,</hi> through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56040:11"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. V. <hi>Of Preparation unto Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>AS there is nothing more certain than death:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.47.</note> 
                     <hi>For what man is there that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth and ſhall not ſee death?</hi> So there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more uncertain than the time of death;
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.36.</note> 
                     <hi>for of that day and hour knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis therefore unknown,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.40.</note> that it might be alway ſuſpected and awaited: <hi>The Son of man cometh in an hour when you think not:</hi> That his coming may be hourly thought upon; <hi>Latet dies ultimus,
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> ut obſerventur omnes dies:</hi> The day of our death is hidden from us, that all our days ſhould be no other but a preparation thereunto, the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the one engaging us unto ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the other
<note n="*" place="margin">Veri ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, nihil aliud quam continua ad mortem praeparatio eſſe debet.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Every danger foreſeen is beſt prevented: And thus death the greateſt of dangers may be rendred the leaſt dangerous by a prudent fear, and careful proviſion for the ſame: <hi>Qui pavet, cavet; qui negligit, incidit:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bern. Prov. 14.16.</note> which may beſt be engliſhed in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>The wiſe man feareth, and departeth from evil; but the fool rageth, and is confident</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Timeat ſemper in vita mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui mortis metum evadere velit.</note>.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56040:12"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>The great end of this mortal life, is to prepare for death; or rather for a ſafe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through death to life Immortal: For upon the well or ill ſpending of the few mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of this preſent life depends either a bleſſed, or a miſerable Eternity.</p>
                  <p>It was the advice of a wiſe man to his friend, to have engraven in capital Letters, in ſome ſuch place of his houſe, as might be moſt frequent in his view, to be often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: <hi>Momentum unde pendet Eternitas.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>There is no conſideration our bleſſed Lord hath ſo frequently inculcated by commands, counſels, exhortations, admonitions, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſimilitudes, arguments and reaſons, as this of <hi>the Chriſtian watch,</hi> i. e. to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, to provide, to be ready, to wait for the coming of the Lord, or for the approach of Death;
<note place="margin">Luke 12.38.</note> whether <hi>he ſhall come in the firſt, or in the ſecond, or in the third watch:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the time of youth, or manhood, or old age:
<note place="margin">Mark 13.34, 35, 36, 37.</note> at all times, and in all ages he commands all men to be upon their watch.</p>
                  <p>This watch implies many particulars, which are ſo many preparatives, unto death.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>To watch,</hi> is to have our eyes open, or our minds enlightned by the holy true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the affections of our hearts, and the actions of our lives be framed according to what we rightly profeſs to believe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 To have our eyes not only opened, but uplifted towards Heaven above, and not ſtill poring upon the Earth below.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56040:12"/>
                  <p n="4">4. In our watch we muſt carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the orders and commands given us by <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Captain of our Salvation.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That we ſhake off all drowzineſs and ſluggiſhneſs, being active and vigorous in the execution of all ſuch commands; and in all the reſpective duties we owe to God and Man.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That when the Lord cometh, and knocketh at the door, by the batteries of death, we be both willing and ready to open unto him: And in order hereunto,</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That our hearts be prepared to receive the Lord, being ſo ſwept and cleanſed, that nothing be found in any corner thereof, which may offend him, who is the ſearcher of all hearts.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. We muſt ſtand upon our watch <hi>with our loins girded,</hi> or all irrational luſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained; that we may be expedite and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to execute whatever our duty to God or Man requires: Thus S. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſtood upon his watch, profeſſing that whether he did eat or drink, reſt or labour, ſleep or wake, he always heard the voice of the laſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounding in his ears, <hi>Awake and come to Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Laſtly, In this watch we muſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, not to be taken off by any wiles of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, concerns of the world, or allurements of the fleſh; but to ſtand fix'd and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in our reſpective ſtations of Chriſtian duty, untill the great Captain and Lord of life and death ſhall remove us hence.</p>
                  <p>And may I thus, bleſſed Lord, continually wait for thy coming, <hi>with my loins girt,</hi> in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56040:13"/>the reſtriction of all the unruly luſts of my heart, and of all the irrational imaginations of my head alſo: and my Lamp of the holy Chriſtian Faith burning continually; being fed with the oil or unction of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and ſhining in and through all the whole courſe of my life, by all ſuch good works as may glorifie thee our Father which art in Heaven. This is that ſacred light (even <hi>faith which worketh by love</hi>) which will infallibly guide me through all the mazes of this mortal life, and convey me ſafely through the gloomy ſhades of death, into the Region of light, and life everlaſting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>In this life our condition is changeable from better to worſe, and from worſe to better: But in death all hopes of bettering our condition are buried with the liveleſs corps.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Now is the acceptable time, now is the day of Salvation.</hi> 'Tis in the day of this life I am commanded <hi>to work out my Salvation with fear and trembling.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil 2.12.</note> When the night of death cometh no man can then work:
<note place="margin">Ecclus 9.10.</note> 
                     <hi>There is neither work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave where thou goeſt.</hi> And it is wiſely therefore adviſed in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words; <hi>Whatever thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might:</hi> Be vigorous, be active,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note> be zealous, <hi>be fruitful in every good work.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Soul that is laden with the fruits of well-doing, ſhall chearfully in the approach of death commit her ſelf <hi>unto God,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. ult.</note> as to a faithful Creator.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56040:13"/>
                  <p>Thoſe good deeds, which through the merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi> will render us ſecure in the hour of death are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Devout and humble, frequent and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers unto God, and praiſes of him, wherein we do moſt immediately both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and commend our Souls unto God, and gain his grace and favour, eſpecially when accompanied with,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Faſtings often:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 2.37.</note> By theſe we offer our bodies in ſacrifice unto God: as by Prayer our Souls.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Charitable Almſdeeds, for with <hi>ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13.15, 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such preparation for death is adviſed by the wiſe <hi>Syracides,</hi> Ecclus. 14.12. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that death will not be long in coming: and that the covenant of the grave is not ſhewed unto thee.</hi> Verſe 13. <hi>Do good to thy friend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou die: put not off to thy laſt Will and Teſtament:</hi> but <hi>according to thy ability ſtretch out thy hand, and give unto the poor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To make the poor our friends, or rather our Acts of charity towards them, againſt the day of death, is commanded by our Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. <hi>Make your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> in the pious and charitable diſtribution of your worldly goods; <hi>that when you fail,</hi> your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies fail to be the habitation of your Souls; <hi>they may receive you into everlaſting habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> Which is yet more fully and plainly commanded by our Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.33, 34, 35, 36. Thus the wiſe Virgins were provided, for the coming of the Bridegroom, with <hi>oil in their Lamps:</hi> their light of Faith was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56040:14"/>kept flaming by charity and good works, by which means they were admitted into the Bridal-chamber of Celeſtial Paradiſe: from whence the fooliſh Virgins were excluded, who had Lamps, but no Oil; Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Charity; or elſe good works without ſincere intentions, and holy affections in the performance of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.3, 4.—</p>
                  <p>'Tis not doubted, but every act of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is tranſient, and every good work of what nature ſoever, takes end with the work done: but the <hi>Charity,</hi> the <hi>Piety,</hi> the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of every religious work is not of a dying ſtamp: <hi>For righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is Immortal,</hi> Wiſd. 1.17.</p>
                  <p>As therefore the good works of holy and good men paſs away and vaniſh, ſo the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> of their actions paſs into Heaven, and ſtand there upon record to plead through the merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for their admiſſion into thoſe Regions of bliſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He hath diſperſed abroad, he hath given to the poor,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 112.9.</note> his righteouſneſs remaineth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; his horn ſhall be exalted with honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed are the dead who die in the Lord; they reſt from their labours,
<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> and their works follow them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord, I pray thee, that thy grace may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way prevent and follow me; and make me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to be given to all good works; the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failing fruits of a true Chriſtian Faith; and by theſe inſeparably conjoyn'd to make my calling and election ſure, ſcaled in the bloud of my dear Redeemer.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56040:14"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There are three general meſſengers of Death: 1. <hi>Chance:</hi> 2. <hi>Sickneſs:</hi> 3. <hi>Old age.</hi> Chance renders the life of man doubtful and uncertain: Sickneſs makes it grievous and weariſo me: Old Age makes it tedious, and Death inevitable.</p>
                  <p>Some perſons are ſtifled in their Mothers womb, and die before they ſee the light of this life.</p>
                  <p>Some die in their infancy, ſome in their youth, ſome in their man's eſtate, and ſome there be, but theſe are of all other the few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in number, who die in their Old age: And yet the moſt of men do not only deſire, but fondly conceit they ſhall live to be old, and yet never think themſelves old enough to die; which makes ſo many millions of perſons die unpreparedly: And ſo paſs from a temporal to death eternal: For death is then moſt generally the neareſt, when 'tis conceited to be furtheſt off.
<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                     <hi>Mors enim propior eſſe ſolet, cum longius abeſſe putetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. 'Tis the thought of a longer, and ſtill of a longer life, that is the great impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Repentance, and amendment of life: whereby the Devil hurries men by throngs to be his woful companions in his Region of blackneſs of darkneſs for ever. And the great Reaſon is, becauſe Repentance delayed till Sickneſs, or Old Age come, is not only uncertain and unſafe, but very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never truly and ſincerely performed. 'Tis a dreadful ſaying of S. <hi>Hierome; That ſcarce one of ten thouſand, who have continued in any ſinful courſe of life, without the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56040:15"/>practice of a true and timely Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, do ever ſo perfectly repent, as to obtain the remiſſion of their ſins in the hour of death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the prevention of ſo great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a miſchief, and perdition of ungodly men; the All-wiſe and good Providence of Heaven hath ordained, that in all ages and conditions of men this life ſhall take end: that ſo none how young and luſty ſoever, with his bones full of marrow, ſhould yet dare to live unprepared for death, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſtill upon further time for Repentance and Amendment of life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tu in ſenectutem ſana defers conſilia, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vitam vis inchoare quo pauci perduxerunt: ſtultitia magna eſt tunc vivere incipere, cum deſinendum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed Lord, ſuffer me not thus to deceive my ſelf, through the ſly inſinuations of Satan, and my own ſenſual inclinations and deſires, but make me ſo mindful of my end, that I may paſs the remainder of my days in the conſtant practice of Repentance, and Godly fear, that living in thy fear, I may die in thy favour, and in a well grounded hope to live with thee for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Every change in my frail conſtitution, every little pain and ache in my corruptible fleſh, all diſtempers and diſeaſes are as ſo many memorials of my mortality; but the older I grow,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8. ult.</note> the nearer ſtill is the approach of my diſſolution by the hand of death; <hi>for that which decayeth and waxeth old is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to vaniſh away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Happy is the man, who on his bed of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56040:15"/>death can ſay with the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7.</note> 
                     <hi>I have fought a good ſight,</hi> againſt all the aſſaults of the Devil, the World and the Fleſh, which war againſt the Soul: <hi>I have finiſhed my courſe:</hi> as the courſe of my life; ſo the courſe of godlineſs in all its reſpective duties enjoyn'd me. <hi>I have kept the Faith,</hi> untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by any Atheiſtical imaginations, heretical opinions, or ſinful practices: and I have been faithful in the diſcharge of thoſe offices, and relations, wherein my great Lord and Maſter hath entruſted and enſtated me.</p>
                  <p>If my heart condemn me not in any of theſe reſpects,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> I may thence conclude with joy and exultation, <hi>from henceforth there is laid up a Crown of righteouſneſs, which the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day; and not to me only, but to all them alſo that love his appearance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Prayer.</head>
                     <p>LOok graciouſly upon me, O Lord, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, in the time of my approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſolution: and the more the outward man decayeth, ſtrengthen me ſo much the more continually by thy Grace and Holy Spirit in the inner man: give me unfeigned repentance for all the errors of my life paſt, and a ſtedfaſt Faith in thy Son <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that my ſins may be done away by thy mercy, and my pardon ſealed in Heaven, before I go hence and be no more ſeen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>IN the midſt of life we be in death: of whom may we ſeek for ſuccour but of thee, O Lord, who for our ſins art juſtly diſpleaſed?</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56040:16"/>
                     <p>Yet, O Lord God moſt holy, O Lord moſt mighty, O holy and moſt merciful Saviour, deliver us not into the bitter pains of eternal Death.</p>
                     <p>Thou knoweſt Lord the ſecrets of our hearts: ſhut not up thy merciful ears to our Prayers, but ſpare us. O Lord moſt holy, O God moſt mighty, O holy and moſt merciful Saviour, thou moſt worthy Judge eternal, ſuffer us not at our laſt hour for any pains of Death to fall from thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>IN my laſt hour, O Lord, I humbly beg thy protection from the buſie ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and direful inſultings of my grand ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Devil and his Angels: Oh let not then my Faith fail, or my Hope wither, or my Charity wax cold with the waining fleſh: but when all my joynts ſhall tremble by the batteries of death, mine eyes be darkned, and my tongue falter, then, O then let my heart be enlarged towards my God, waiting upon thee, longing for thee, and inceſſantly praying, <hi>ſhew me thy mercy, O Lord, and grant me thy Salvation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:56040:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> XXXIX. <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Verſes,</head>
               <p n="1">1. I <hi>Said, I will take heed to my ways: that I offend not in my tongue</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of death makes every wiſe man careful of all his ways, and more eſpecially to avoid the offences of the tongue.</note>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>I will keep my mouth as 'twere with a bridle: while the ungodly is in my ſight</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The tongue is an unruly evil, and muſt be tam'd as a wild horſe with a bridle, eſpecially when provok'd by captious, contentious and quarrelſome perſons.</note>.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>I held my tongue, and ſpake nothing: I kept ſilence, yea even from good words, but it was pain and grief unto me</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches are for the moſt part beſt anſwered with a diſcreet ſilence; ſo was our Lord, as a Lamb, dumb before the Shearers.</note>.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>My heart was hot within, and while I was thus muſing, the fire kindled
<note n="*" place="margin">To ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from good words is ſometimes neceſſary for the avoiding of an evil conſtruction: but ſuch ſilence is grievous to the pious Soul, which burns with the fire of divine love, and zeal to God's glory. <hi>The zeal of thine houſe hath even eaten me up.</hi>
                     </note>: and at the laſt I ſpake with my tongue</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Though it be often inconvenient to ſpeak before wicked Men, yet it is alway neceſſary to ſpeak unto God by Prayer.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56040:17"/>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Lord, let me know mine end, and the number of my days: that I may be certified how long I have to live</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">'Tis a bleſſing we ought alway to pray for, to be feelingly ſenſible of the ſhortneſs of our life.</note>.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Behold thou haſt made my days as 'twere a ſpan long; and mine age is nothing in reſpect of thee: and verily every man living is altogether vanity</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The life of man if compar'd with God's everlaſting Being, is rather to be called a death than a life, a vanity, not a verity of being.</note>.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>For man walketh in a vain ſhadow, he diſquieteth himſelf in vain: he heapeth up riches, and cannot tell who ſhall gather them</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The hearts of men are darkned with the ſhadows of happineſs, whilſt they vainly care for worldly wealth, which is as tranſitory and uncertain as the life it ſelf.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:56040:17"/>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>And now, Lord, what is my hope? truly my hope is even in thee</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">'Tis not in riches, nor in all the world affords, but in God alone that all hope of true happineſs is attainable.</note>.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Deliver me from all mine offences: and make me not a rebuke to the fooliſh</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Our ſins deprive us of all true well-grounded hopes in God: and make us liable to the ſcorn, even of fooliſh men.</note>.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>I became dumb, and opened not my mouth: for it was thy doing</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">We muſt with a patient ſilence ſuffer the reproaches of others, becauſe occaſioned by our offences, and becauſe ſent from God for our amendment.</note>.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Take thy plague away from me: I am even conſumed by the means of thy heavy hand</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">And confeſs withal, that we deſerve to be conſumed by the juſt judgments of God.</note>.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>When thou with rebukes doſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man for ſin, thou makeſt his beauty to conſume away, as 'twere a moth fretting a garment: every man therefore is but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Whoſe lighteſt chaſtiſements do eaſily deface the beauty, and decay the ſtrength of the corruptible body.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56040:18"/>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Hear my prayer, O Lord, and with thine ear conſider my calling: hold not thy peace at my tears</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the devout Soul is poured forth in Prayers, with tears of godly ſorrow for her offences, from whence all the miſeries of this life do flow.</note>.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>For I am a ſtranger with thee: and a ſojourner as all my fathers were</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The earth is a ſtrange land to the immortal Soul, whoſe native home is Heaven, where ſhe was framed by the hands of the Almighty after his own Image.</note>.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>O ſpare me a little that I may reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my ſtrength, before I go hence and be no more ſeen</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Which Image being defaced by her ſins, ſhe humbly begs with tears, Time and Space by Repentance, Faith and new Obedience, to recover her native ſtrength and beauty, before ſhe leave her tabernacle of fleſh.</note>.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>SInce my days are but as a ſpan, ſhort and uncertain, I humbly beſeech thee, O Lord, to wean my heart from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude of worldly cares: and that I may
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56040:18"/>be fruitful in all the good works of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and charity, to repair the breaches of thy bleſſed Image which mine offences have made, before my departure hence: that ſo recovering the ſpiritual health and ſtrength of my Soul, I may die in thy Grace and Favour, through <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="Psalm">
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> XC. <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Verſes,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>LOrd, thou haſt been our Refuge from one generation to another</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Holy men have in all ages of the world applied themſelves unto the Lord for ſuccour, ſupport and protection in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</note>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Before the mountains were brought forth, or ever the earth and the world were made: thou art God from everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and world without end</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Who being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal is alſo immutable in his mercy, goodneſs, power and providence over all.</note>.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Thou turneſt man to deſtruction: again thou ſayſt, Come again ye children of men</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing both health and ſickneſs, proſperity and adverſity, life and death to the ſons of men, according to his all-juſt, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful, all-wiſe good pleaſure.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56040:19"/>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>For a thouſand years in thy ſight are but as yeſterday: ſeeing that is paſt as a watch in the night</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The longeſt courſe of man's life in reſpect of God's eternal praevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is but as a day that is already paſt, or as one of the night-watches, which is both ſwift and ſhort, and alſo dark and gloomy through frequent, croſs and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe occurrents.</note>.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>As ſoon as thou ſcattereſt them, they are even aſleep: and fade away ſuddenly as the graſs</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">As ſleep is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of death, ſo the life of man in this world is but the image or ſhadow of life, for as a ſhadow it fleeth the purſuer and fadeth as the graſs.</note>.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>In the morning it is green, and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up: in the evening it is cut down, dried up and withered</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Which the ſame day beholds both growing and cut down, flouriſhing and withered.</note>.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>For we conſume away in thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: and are afraid at thy wrathful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This frailty of humane life is the puniſhment of ſin, which incurs moſt juſtly God's indignation and wrath.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56040:19"/>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Thou haſt ſet our miſ-deeds before thee: and our ſecret ſins in the light of thy countenance</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Whoſe eyes are ten thouſand times brighter than the Sun, both ſeeing and recording the moſt ſecret of our ſinful ways.</note>.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>For when thou art angry, all our days are gone: we bring our years to an end, as it were a tale that is told</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">'Tis through God's juſt anger for our ſins, that our days are ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and our years are ſpent in vanity and trouble.</note>.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>The days of our age are threeſcore years and ten: and though men be ſo ſtrong that they come to fourſcore years, yet is their ſtrength then but labour and ſorrow: ſo ſoon paſſeth it away and we are gone</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The miſeries of man's life are not ſo great through the ſhortneſs thereof, as that his ſorrows, and troubles are increaſed with his days.</note>.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>But who regardeth the power of thy wrath? for even thereafter as a man fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſo is thy diſpleaſure</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">God's diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for our ſins is either more or leſs, according as we do leſs or more ſtand in awe thereof.</note>.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>So teach us to number our days: that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">True wiſdom is attained by the ſerious contemplation of the frailty of life and certainty of death.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56040:20"/>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Turn thee again, O Lord, at the laſt: and be gracious unto thy ſervants</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixing with our meditations devout Prayers for the propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous grace and favour of God.</note>.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>O ſatisfie us with thy mercy, and that ſoon: ſo ſhall we rejoyce and be glad all the days of our life</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Which alone can ſatisfie the deſires of the immortal Soul, and throughly rejoyce the ſame.</note>.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Comfort us again now after the time thou haſt plagued us: and for the years wherein we have ſuffered adverſity</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">We may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably alledge our ſufferings, though for our ſins, as motives to implore the conſolations of God's Spirit.</note>.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Shew thy ſervants thy work: and their children thy glory</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">God's proper work is mercy, and 'tis his glory to be gracious, for the which the righteous do pray both for themſelves and their Children.</note>.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>And the glorious Majeſty of the Lord our God be upon us: proſper thou the work of our hands upon us, proſper thou our handy work</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">God's glorious Majeſty appears by the gracious influences of his holy Spirit: whereby we work the works of God, to his glory and our own eternal happineſs.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:56040:20"/>
               <q>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God, the Fountain of all Wiſdom, grant me ſo wiſely to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and compare the ſhort and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful days of this mortal Life, with that joyful and never ending day of a bleſſed eternity; that deſpiſing the vanities of the one, I may zealouſly aſpire to the happineſs of the other. O ſatisfie the panting deſires of my Soul, with the ſenſe of thy mercy in the pardon of my ſins: and let the glory of thy grace appear, in proſpering me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all thoſe good works of Faith and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which conduce to my eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, through <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="particular judgment" type="meditations">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:56040:21"/>
            <head>THE Second general Meditation UPON JUDGMENT. And firſt the Particular Judgment.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>
                  <hi>IT is appointed unto man once to die,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> and after that the Judgment:</hi> No ſooner ſhall this houſe of fleſh, wherein the immortal Soul doth now inhabit, be ſhattered in pieces by the hand of death, but in the ſame moment the departing Soul ſhall be conveyed by the Angels of God before his Judgment-ſeat: and this is call'd <hi>The particular Judgment,</hi> that ſhall paſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every perſon in particular immediately upon his death:
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7.</note> 
                  <hi>when the duſt ſhall return to the earth as it was, then ſhall the Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto God that gave it:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> To give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the works done in the body, whether they be good, or whether they be evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56040:21"/>
               <p>That grand enemy of man, the Devil, awaits thy Soul's departure hence, to dog thee to the great Tribunal of Heaven.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ille enim tunc ſaevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens capit quos nunc blandiens decipit.</hi> Greg.</note> 
                  <hi>In this life he fawns to ſeduce, but in the other he will roar to devour, as a Lion over his prey:</hi> to this end he will vehemently accuſe thee, aggravating all thy miſcarriages through his ſuggeſtions committed, and claiming thee as one of the ſubjects of his kingdom of darkneſs: ſaying to the great Judge of all, as ſeveral Fathers obſerve:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">"This perſon (thou Judge of the world) though he be thine by <hi>Creation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſſ. Hom. Aug. orat. cont. Judaos, Pag.</note> yet he is mine by <hi>Depravation:</hi> He is Thine by <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> but mine by <hi>ſin,</hi> for he has obeyed my ſuggeſtions, and diſobeyed thy Laws: and therefore though he belong to thee by <hi>right,</hi> yet he is faln to me by <hi>default:</hi> he is thine in reſpect of his <hi>workmanſhip,</hi> but mine by <hi>the rebellion of his will,</hi> and <hi>diſorder</hi> of his <hi>affections:</hi> having yielded himſelf to follow my temptations, and to forſake the paths of thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But 'tis not the Devil alone that ſhall thus accuſe thee when arraigned at the Bar of divine Judgment: but (as S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith) the Heavens and the Earth, and the Sea, the Sun and the Moon and the Stars, both Nights and Days, and all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thou haſt abuſed, ſhall bear witneſs againſt thee: but above all,</p>
               <p>Thine own Conſcience ſhall be as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes; for being then freed from this clog and damp of the corruptible fleſh, all thy imaginations and deſires, all thy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56040:22"/>words and works ſpoken and done in the body, ſhall appear to thy Conſcience in their native, genuine and proper colours, without any ignorance or oblivion, miſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion or miſpriſion, which now blinds the minds of many thouſands to their eternal ruine on that day.</p>
               <p>O who ſhall then be able to anſwer thee one of a thouſand (thou moſt worthy Judge eternal) if thou ſhouldſt be extream to mark what is done amiſs,
<note place="margin">Job 9.2. Pſ. 130.3.</note> and thy great mercy intervene not to mitigate the rigor of thy Juſtice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in thee have I put my truſt:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 38.15,</note> Thou ſhalt anſwer for me, O Lord my God.</hi> I have no other Advocate to plead my cauſe, but my righteous Judge himſelf from whom in my daily prayers <hi>I have required that they,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> even mine enemies, ſhould not triumph over me,</hi> when I ſtand to be judged before the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 23.2, 3.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">"Who will ſet ſcourges over my thoughts, and the diſcipline of wiſdom over my heart, that they ſpare me not for mine ignorances, and paſs not by my ſins? Leſt mine ignorances increaſe, and my ſins abound to my deſtruction: And I fall before mine adverſaries (in the day of my trial) <hi>and mine enemies</hi> (the ſpirits and powers of darkneſs) <hi>rejoyce over me, whoſe hope is far from thy mercy.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Meditat.</hi> II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>My fleſh trembleth for fear of thee,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.120.</note> and I am afraid of thy Judgments:</hi> when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56040:22"/>the ſeverity of many of thy temporal judgments, which are now intended to drive ſinners to Repentance, that thou mighteſt ſpare them hereafter, I cannot but foreſee the unconceivable rigour of thy eternal judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which intend puniſhment only, without any thought of future mercy to ſpare and to forgive, as in this life.</p>
               <p>And I vile ſinner have great cauſe to fear, as a ſtrict examination which all muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo, ſo ſevere a ſentence to paſs upon me, having not ſo conſcienciouſly as I ought obeyed the ſacred dictates of <hi>the ſaving grace of God, teaching us,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2, 11, 12, 13.</note> that denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With what face then ſhall I look for the bleſſed hope, or hope for bleſſedneſs upon the appearance of the great God and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt?</p>
               <p>I have a greater cauſe to fear, than to hope; to wave, than to await his coming.</p>
               <p>But how ſhall I avoid, or whither ſhall I flee from the face of my Judge? whither but from an offended God, to a merciful Redeemer? from the Throne of thy Juſtice, to thy Mercy-ſeat? To meet thee now with Repentance in my heart, and the fruits thereof brought forth in the actions of my life; and with ſuch ſpiritual wings cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the bloud of my Redeemer, I may hope to flee from the wrath to come.</p>
               <p>O God who art juſtly diſpleaſed for our ſins,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.7, 8.</note> and pacified by our true and ſincere Repentance; ſpare, O ſpare all thoſe who confeſs their ſins unto thee: that they whoſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56040:23"/>conſciences by ſin are accuſed, by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful pardon may be abſolved through Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Meditat.</hi> III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before Judgment examine thy ſelf:
<note place="margin">Eccl. 18.20.</note> and in the day of viſitation thou ſhalt find mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I, upon the examination of my ſelf do find my heart foul and polluted, and my life ſtain'd with manifold offences: but that I may eſcape the judgment of God, I judge my ſelf to be a miſerable ſinner, I judge my ſelf to have incurr'd the Lord's juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to have deſerved the diſmal ſentence of condemnation to paſs upon me. <hi>For I have ſinned, and I have done wickedly, and I have committed iniquity, and have rebelled againſt the Lord by departing from his moſt holy Laws and Judgments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many will be my accuſers when I come to my great Trial upon life or death eternal: and many and great accuſations have they to lay againſt me: the Devil and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, whoſe ſuggeſtions unto evil I have too often followed; many men, and many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men too who have been conſcious of my ſins, and of whoſe ſins I have been many ways guilty: All the good Creatures of God I have abuſed, and his mercies in them: all thoſe evil deeds I have committed, and the many good offices I have wittingly omitted, all which ſtand upon record in the Lord's black book of remembrance: and mine own Conſcience ſhall bear witneſs to all theſe undeniable Evidences.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:56040:23"/>
               <p>Theſe are the Books that ſhall be opened againſt me: and I have not what to anſwer for my ſelf:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.1.</note> 
                  <hi>But my truſt is in the tender mercies of the Lord, therefore I ſhall not fall,</hi> and be caſt in my trial. Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who waſt condemned being innocent, acquit me though greatly nocent through Faith in thy Bloud.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judge me, O Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 35.24,</note> according to thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> not after mine; for 'tis little, and good for little: but 'tis thy righteouſneſs, Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> both active and paſſive, I muſt plead for my acquittance when judged by thee: then, O then <hi>let not mine enemies tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let them not ſay in their hearts, there,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> there, ſo would we have it: neither let them ſay, we have devoured him:</hi> But in the hour of death and in the day of Judgment,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="general judgment" type="meditations">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56040:24"/>
            <head>MEDITATIONS UPON THE <hi>General Judgment.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHen the Son of man ſhall come in his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.31,</note> and all his holy Angels with him, then ſhall he ſit upon the Throne of his Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And before him all nations ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi>—
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/>
            </p>
            <p>This is called <hi>The day of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.2.</note> by way of Eminence, as being of all days the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>And that firſt in reſpect of the great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance which ſhall be upon this day, both of the Judge and the perſons to be judged.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Great and glorious, terrible and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſhall be the appearance of the Judge himſelf, with all his numerous attendants.</p>
               <p>His perſonal appearance ſhall be in Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and great glory; not in reſpect of his Divine nature, for that appears not to the eyes of fleſh; but in reſpect of his Humane nature aſſumed.</p>
               <p>That nature which appear'd here upon earth, poor, mean, contemptible: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was deſpiſed and ſcorned, whipt and ſcourged, beaten and buffetted, beſpatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with ignominious ſpittings and vile re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56040:24"/>rack'd, disjoynted, diſtorted, deformed, nailed and pierced, crucified and died: ſhall upon this day appear cloathed with Majeſty and crowned with glory: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very eye ſhall ſee him, even they alſo who pierced him; and the marks in his nailed hands, in his nailed feet, and in his gored ſide ſhall appear as ſo many ſhining Stars for their glittering ſplendor.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A great day in reſpect of the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous attendants upon this great Judge; of whom <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9.—<hi>when the ancient of days did ſit— thouſand thouſands miniſtred unto him, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand ſtood before him; the judgment was ſet, and the books were opened.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When this day of the Lord cometh, the Sun ſhall be turned into darkneſs, and the Moon into bloud; and all the glittering Stars ſhall fall from their Orbs: but then the Sun of righteouſneſs ſhall ſhine, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by all the triumphing Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of Heaven, who ſhall appear as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Stars in the Firmament above, dazling the eyes, and aſtoniſhing the hearts of all perſons to be judged; and this renders,</p>
               <p n="3">3. This day a great day in reſpect of the appearance that ſhall then be; even of all the Men that ever lived, or ſhall live upon the face of the earth: and of all the Angels alſo, who are more numerous than men in the judgment of the Schoolman; who ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>T. Aq. p.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 50. <hi>Art.</hi> 3.</note> that there be as many, if not more, of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual than of corporal Beings.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56040:25"/>
               <p n="4">4. A great day in reſpect of the multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous Trials, even of all the works that ever have been done, from the Creation to the diſſolution of all things under the Sun.</p>
               <p>And not our works only; but,</p>
               <p n="5">5. Of all our words, even of every idle word an account muſt be given: <hi>By thy words thou ſhalt be juſtified,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.36, 37.</note> and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Not our words and works only, but even the inward <hi>thoughts, intentions,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires</hi> of our hearts ſhall be expos'd to open view and cenſure: <hi>the Lord will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and will make manifeſt the counſels of all hearts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt ſeared Conſcience of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the moſt ſubtle ſecret Conſcience of the Hypocrite, ſhall by the all-piercing light of the divine Majeſty be diſplayed, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as manifeſt and open, as if all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels thereof had been written with a beam of the Sun:
<note place="margin">Pſ 90.8.</note> 
                  <hi>For thou, O Lord, haſt ſet our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds before thee, and our ſecret ſins in the light of thy countenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis recorded of <hi>Agathon,</hi> a perſon fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous amongſt the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Fathers for ſtrictneſs and holineſs of life, that he was notwithſtanding exceedingly afraid upon his approaching death: And being demanded the reaſon of his fear by ſuch as knew the innocence of his life: He anſwered, That the judgments of God do vaſtly differ from the judgments of Men: <hi>Every way of man is right in his own eyes, but the Lord weigheth the ſpirits,</hi> Prov. 16.2. Woe, woe to the moſt holy and innocent life amongſt Men,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56040:25"/>if the mercy of God do not interpoſe in the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>For alas, who is ſo holy, who ſo pure and innocent, as to ſtand with any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in that all-diſcerning light of the Sun of Righteouſneſs?
<note place="margin">Eccl. 23.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſe eyes are a thouſand times brighter than the Sun, beholding all the ways of men, and conſidering their moſt ſecret parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have been guilty (moſt merciful Father) I have been guilty of manifold miſcarriages, which I have now forgotten, nor can I through the ſtricteſt examination of my ſelf, recal to my memory many of mine offences.
<note place="margin">Job 14.16, 17.</note> But although I cannot, <hi>yet thou numbreſt my ſteps: doſt thou not watch over my ſin?— my tranſgreſſion is ſealed up in a bag, and thou ſoweſt up mine iniquities.</hi> So ſurely are all my tranſgreſſions kept in ſtore againſt the day of my Trial: whilſt I ſenſual and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, think all is well enough with me, and that my ſins are forgotten:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 19.12.</note> 
                  <hi>O cleanſe thou me from all my ſecret faults:</hi> and as they are hid from my memory,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 51.9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo hide thou thy face from them;</hi> blot them out of thy Book of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that they appear not to my confuſion on that great and laſt day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yea even the wicked for the day of evil, Prov.</hi> 16.4. The great day of Judgment is call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the day of evil:</hi> As for which day the Lord hath reſerved the full execution of his ſevere juſtice upon all the evils of the world.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:56040:26"/>
               <p>In the Creation of all things, <hi>the power of God</hi> was moſt eſpecially manifeſted: in the government of the world doth <hi>his wiſdom</hi> moſt appear: In the Redemption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind <hi>his mercy</hi> is moſt tranſparent: And in the day of Judgment ſhall <hi>his juſtice</hi> moſt eminently ſhew forth and exerciſe its ſtrict and ſevereſt meaſures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sad and diſmal is the ſentence that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this great day ſhall paſs upon all ſuch, whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> hath not according to ability and opportunity been fruitful in the good works of Charity:
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.41, 42.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire—For I was an hungred and ye gave me no meat—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if theſe ſhall be eternally damned, who have not given of their own goods for the relief of others: what ſhall become of the Oppreſſor, the Extortioner, the Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Thief, and of every one who either by force or fraud, publickly or ſecretly, hath either taken, or detained what of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto others? Surely if the one ſhall go, the other ſhall be driven, hurried with a vengeance into everlaſting fire.
<note place="margin">Ver. ult.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Great, unconceivably great ſhall be the perplexity and anguiſh of the impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner in this great day: beholding (as <hi>Anſelm</hi> meditates) on the <hi>one ſide</hi> his ſins ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him, and <hi>on the other</hi> the ſtrict and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial juſtice of Heaven, ready to paſs ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon him: ſeeing <hi>below</hi> him the mouth of Hell gaping to devour him; and <hi>above</hi> him an angry Judge condemning him to that place of Horror: feeling <hi>within</hi> an accuſing Conſcience tormenting him, and <hi>without</hi> the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56040:26"/>whole world in conſuming flames:
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>And if the righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſav'd, where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appear?</hi> or where ſhall he hide himſelf that he may not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? For any wicked one to lie hidden on that day is impoſſible, and to appear is dreadful and intolerable.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, that the very ſight of an angry Judge ſhall be then more unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable than a thouſand Hells.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This is that diſmal day foretold by our Lord himſelf, wherein <hi>they ſhall ſay, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the barren,
<note place="margin">Luke 23.29,</note> and the womb that never bare, and the paps which never gave ſuck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then ſhall they begin to ſay to the mountains,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> fall on us, and to the hills, cover us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And hide us from the face of him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon the throne,
<note place="margin">Rev. 6.16.</note> and from the wrath of the Lamb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the great day of his wrath is come:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Woe is me that I have ſinned: woe, woe, is me, that I have offended this great and terrible Judge of all the world: but as is his Majeſty, ſo is his Mercy great and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>Have mercy upon me, O God, on that great day, have mercy upon me: and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me now in this world from the ſociety, from the temptations, from the guilt of the wicked;
<note place="margin">Pſ. 141.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Let me not be occupied in any ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly works with the men that work wickedneſs,</hi> that I be not reckoned and ranked amongſt them in the world to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:56040:27"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The day of Judgment is not only of all days the moſt dreadful, but the moſt joyful alſo.</p>
               <p>The righteous, and the holy, and the juſt ſhall appear in glorified bodies, encir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled with the ſhining rays of exceſſive light; but the wicked in bodies, or carcaſſes rather both hideous and loathſome.</p>
               <p>To the impenitent and wicked of the world, 'tis a day of the greateſt terror; but to the holy and humble of heart and life, a day of Jubilee and greateſt joy: a day of ſhame and confuſion to the one, of glory and conſolation to the other.</p>
               <p>How great then ſhall be the glory of the holy Chriſtian; and how great the ſhame of infidelity and Atheiſm! how great the joy of the true Believer, whoſe Faith has been fruitful in all good words; and how great the ſorrow of the Heretick, Hypocrite, the profane and diſſolute! for then, and not fully till <hi>then ſhall God render to every man according to his works.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.7,</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To them who by patient continuing in well doing, do ſeek for glory, and honour, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: eternal life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to them who are contentious,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8,"/> and obey not the truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs: indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and wrath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tribulation,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9,"/> and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man that doth evil: of the Jew firſt, and alſo of the Gentile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But glory,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10,"/> honour and peace, to every man that worketh good.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:56040:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For there is no reſpect of perſons with God.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>What heart can worthily think of theſe things, without trembling and great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, if not purified and ſincerely devoted to the ſervice of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teach me, O Lord, thy way,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 86.11.</note> and I will walk in thy truth: O knit my heart unto thee that I may fear thy name:</hi> fear to offend thee the great and righteous Judge of the world, in the leaſt particular of thought or deſire, of word or of deed.</p>
               <p>Lord, who never faileſt to help and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them whom thou doſt bring up in thy ſtedfaſt fear and love: keep us, we beſeech thee under the protection of thy good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and make us to have a perpetual fear and love of thy holy name, through <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the Son of man cometh,
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.8.</note> ſhall he find faith upon the earth?</hi> All we who are called Chriſtians, profeſs to believe both the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain coming of Chriſt to Judgment, and the uncertainty of the time: That we muſt all ſtand before his dreadful Tribunal and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive every man according to his works: but this is generally a dead Faith, it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens not the affections, it excites not to ſuch holy conſcientious actions, as the firm and cordial Belief of all this does imply and command: and ſo will prove as dangerous to the Souls of ſuch Believers as if they had no faith at all.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56040:28"/>
               <p>With moſt of men the Judgments of God, and all the amazing concerns of Eternity, are no more but words which they hear: they have but very narrow, very ſhallow and dark conceptions of them: they underſtand not their great aſtoniſhing importance; and are not therefore deeply affected therewith to become wiſe unto Salvation.</p>
               <p>O raiſe up thy ſtupid Soul, I do here ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon there whoſoever thou art that regardeſt theſe Meditations, and thou art hereby ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd particularly as by name to make thy appearance at this general Aſſizes to be held at the great and laſt day; and there to give an account of every paſſage throughout thy whole life: which ſhall be as ſtrictly and throughly ſifted and examined, as if there were none but thy ſelf to be tried, as if no cauſe but thine alone were to be heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eja Chariſſime</hi>—Conſider my dear Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brother, out of what great danger thou mayſt now deliver thy ſelf, and from what great fear thou mayſt be freed, if now thou doſt alway ſtand in awe and ſin not; if now thou beeſt alway ſuſpectful of death, and ſolicitous of the Judgment to come. <hi>T. K. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Prepare then, prepare thy ſelf now; now that thou haſt time and leiſure prepare thy ſelf for that great day; for upon thy Trial then depends either thy everlaſting well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31. Jam. 4.8, 9, 10. Act. 10.4. Luk 2.37. 2 Cor. 11.27.</note> or miſerable undoing for ever. Now then caſt up thy accounts carefully; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, try, and judge thy ſelf; confeſs thy manifold amiſſes: Humble thy ſelf greatly under the mighty hand of God: Appeaſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56040:28"/>the wrath of the great Judge of the world by Prayers and Tears,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.17.</note> and all the ſacred of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and acts of true Repentance, by Alms and Offerings and Faſtings often: and in a word,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5.</note> by all the kinds of thoſe <hi>ſpiritual ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices that are acceptable unto God through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Stir up, we beſeech thee, O Lord, the wills of thy fatithful people: quicken our dead and cold Faith with the ſacred fire of holy Charity, the very bond of perfection and all vertue, that we plenteouſly bringing forth the fruits of good works, may of thee be plenteouſly rewarded at the laſt day, through <hi>Jeſus—</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And there was a cry at midnight,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.6.</note> Behold the bridegroom cometh:</hi> Woe unto me then (ſaith a devout Father) if I be found ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my bed at midnight,
<note place="margin">Ambr. in Luc.</note> when the great Judge of all the world ſhall appear: it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns me much rather to reſolve with holy <hi>David:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.62.</note> at midnight I will riſe to give thanks unto thee, becauſe of thy righteous Indgments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Happy are thoſe ſervants whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find upon their watch,
<note place="margin">Mar. 13.33, 34.</note> awaiting his coming with their <hi>loins girt,</hi> their luſts reſtrained, and <hi>their Lamps burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> The light of the holy and true Faith flaming by divine Love, and ſhining through all the actions of their life:
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.26.</note> 
                  <hi>that others ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their good works may glorifie God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:56040:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will ſtand upon my watch</hi> to guard the innocency of my Soul:
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41.</note> I will watch and alſo pray, that I fall not into the ſnare of the Devil when tempted by him: and that day come upon me unawares.</p>
               <p>There be two ſorts of ſins eſpecially, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which my bleſſed Redeemer hath commanded me to watch, that the day of the Lord ſurprize me not: Firſt, <hi>Surfeiting and Drunkenneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 21.34.</note> or the pleaſures of the fleſh. Secondly, <hi>The cares of the world,</hi> or Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Covetouſneſs: againſt theſe grand enemies, which continually war againſt my Soul, it concerns me continually alſo to watch and pray.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed Lord, let not, I humbly beſeech thee, any importunate cravings of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible fleſh ſeduce me, nor the flattering falſe felicities of worldly wealth and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deceive me; but grant that I being free from all pollutions both from the one, and the other, may await thy coming in all holy but humble confidence, to be ranked not amongſt the curſed goats on thy left hand, but amongſt thy bleſſed Sheep on the right hand, and hear that joyful ſentence ſaying, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, receive the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prepared for you from the beginning of the world:</hi> Grant this O heavenly Father.—</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Our Father which art in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:56040:29"/>
               <head>The XXVI. PSALM. PARAPHRASED.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BE thou my judge, O Lord:</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>1</label> not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me for my ſins, but to accept of my ſervices, though imperfect and weak? <hi>for I have walked innocently:</hi> not according to the Innocency of thy Saints in Heaven, but according to that of frail Man upon Earth. Neither do I herein preſume to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie my ſelf, but <hi>my truſt hath been alſo in the Lord:</hi> 'tis not my innocency, but the Lord's mercy I rely upon, and <hi>therefore ſhall I not fall</hi> in the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examine me, O Lord, and prove me:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> now is the time, aſſiſted by thy all-piercing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to examine my ſelf, in order to my grand examination in that day: <hi>Try out my reins and my heart;</hi> as the ſilver is tried when the droſs is purged out, and this even in the furnace of affliction if it ſo ſeemeth good unto thee: that my reins and my heart may be cleanſed from all filthineſs both of fleſh and ſpirit; and yet even ſo I dare not undergo thy ſtrict and ſevere examination of me, but with reflections upon thine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thy loving kindneſs is ever before mine eyes:</hi> 'Tis my conſtant meditation,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> my hope and my refuge: <hi>and I will walk in thy truth:</hi> inwardly delighting and outwardly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the commands thereof: and that I may do this,</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:56040:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have not dwelt with vain perſons,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> made my abode with ſuch as follow the pomps and vanities of this wicked world: <hi>neither will I have fellowſhip with the deceitful:</hi> I have not ſo delighted in the ſociety, as to be tainted by the evil examples of ſuch as through their deceivable luſts keep not the Covenant they have made with their God: nor is it enough to avoid the ſociety, but</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have hated the congregation of the wicked:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> not their perſons but their wickedneſs and all their conſultations to do evil: <hi>and will not ſit among the ungodly,</hi> ſo as to continue and be delighted with the errors of their ways.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will waſh my hands in innocency,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> O Lord:</hi> with the tears of true Repentance I will waſh the ſinful works of my hands, and keep them clean and innocent for the future: <hi>and ſo,</hi> not in my ſins unrepented, <hi>will I go to thine Altar</hi> to offer up Vows and Prayers with the precious body and bloud of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That I may ſhew the voice of thanksgiving:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> publickly declare the great Thanks and Praiſe which is due to thy divine Majeſty: <hi>and tell of all thy wondrous works:</hi> joyning with the Miniſters of thy Temple in Pſalms and Hymns and ſpiritual ſongs, wherein thy great works both of Mercy and Judgment are celebrated.</p>
               <p>To this end,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
                  <hi>Lord, I have loved, the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thy houſe,</hi> the place where thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiteſt more eſpecially than any other hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and 'tis my delight to come to this houſe, becauſe 'tis <hi>the place where thine
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56040:30"/>honour dwelleth:</hi> where the honour of thy Name is continually celebrated: for <hi>in his Temple doth every man ſpeak of his Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince 'tis the joy of my heart to joyn with thy people in the praiſe of thy Name,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  <hi>O ſhut not up my ſoul with the ſinners:</hi> though in this world I cannot altogether eſcape their temptation and trouble, yet rank me not amongſt them, in the world to come: <hi>nor my life with the bloud-thirſty:</hi> let me not periſh with the cruel, uncharitable and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In whoſe hands is wickedneſs:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> the works of whoſe hands are unjuſt, and deſtructive: <hi>and their right hand is full of gifts:</hi> even their righteous actions are for bribes, and ſiniſter ends tranſacted: and ſuch are all they who make a gain of godlineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But as for me,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> though others purſue their worldly intereſt through injuſtice and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery: yet <hi>I will walk innocently:</hi> that's the deſire and reſolution of my Soul: <hi>O deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me,</hi> through the precious bloud of my Redeemer, which was ſhed for my delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; defend me from all my ghoſtly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that would deſtroy mine innocence: <hi>and be merciful unto me:</hi> let thy mercy both pardon my by-paſt tranſgreſſions, and ſupport me through all the perils of this mortal life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My foot ſtandeth right</hi> fixed in my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to cleave unto thee,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> and <hi>I will praiſe the Lord in the congregations:</hi> in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Lord's people, in the houſe where his Honour dwelleth: and ſo ſhall I hope to be hereafter admitted into the bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56040:31"/>company of Angels and Saints to praiſe the Lord for ever: ſaying,
<q>
                     <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="Psalm">
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> XLIII. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> PARAPHRASED.</head>
               <p>Verſe, 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIve ſentence with me, O God:</hi> when I ſtand before thee to be judged accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my works done in the body, whether good or evil, O then <hi>defend my cauſe againſt the ungodly people:</hi> Plead for me againſt all the accuſations of men, women, devils, in whoſe company, or by whoſe temptations I have done any evil: <hi>O deliver me from the deceitful and wicked man,</hi> that I be not ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked amongſt ſuch upon the left hand of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs and infelicity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thou art the God of my ſtrength:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By whom I am enabled to reſiſt all my ghoſtly enemies: <hi>why haſt thou put me from thee</hi> leaving me to mine own weak, frail and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſelf? And this is the reaſon, <hi>why I go ſo heavily,</hi> in the ways of thy ſervice and of mine own ſalvation: <hi>whilſt the enemy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56040:31"/>me;</hi> being deſtitute of thy help, the grand enemy of God and Man over-powers me with his temptations and aſſaults: But that I may manfully reſiſt and overcome,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O ſend out thy light and thy truth,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the light of thy Grace, and the truth of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which diſcerns the cauſe of the righteous from the ungodly, <hi>that they may lead me</hi> out of all the errours of this ſinful life; that being ſeparated from the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſociety of the ungodly, they <hi>may bring me to thy holy hill,</hi> where thy Temple is ſituate, <hi>and to thy dwelling,</hi> the place where thine honour dwelleth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that I may go to the Altar of God</hi> both Sacramental, and Myſtical:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> upon the Altar of my heart to offer up my whole ſelf, to be a living Sacrifice, Holy, acceptable unto God, <hi>even the God of my joy and gladneſs,</hi> who makes glad my heart by the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Holy Spirit, when I approach his Altar: <hi>and upon the Harp,</hi> which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of a Triangular figure, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the heart of man: wherewithal <hi>I will give thanks unto thee,</hi> O holy and ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, <hi>one God</hi> over all, bleſſed for ever, and <hi>my God,</hi> even the God of my joy and worſhip, my Glory and my Crown? O then</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why art thou ſo heavy, O my ſoul?</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> There is no ſorrow but for ſin, becauſe this alone ſeparateth the Soul from the God of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: <hi>and why art thou ſo diſquieted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me?</hi> 'Tis thy unquiet paſſions, and unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, which diſturb thy reaſon, and withdraw thee thus diſquieted from a ſincere
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56040:32"/>dependance upon thy God: but return, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto thy reſt, O my Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O put thy truſt in God:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> all thy ſorrows and diſtempers are from thy ſelf, thy health and joy is from the Lord: and for this <hi>I will yet give him thanks:</hi> who is to be praiſed in both the ſeaſons of ſadneſs and joy: for in both,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He is the help of my countenance,</hi> the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome gladneſs of my heart, <hi>and my God,</hi> both of my Being and Well-being, even the God of all that I am, and all that I have, and all that I hope to be; which is to enjoy the beatifical viſion of his divine Majeſty: for ever to ſing,
<q>
                     <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="pains of hell" type="meditation">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:56040:32"/>
            <head>THE Third General Meditation UPON THE PAINS of HELL.</head>
            <p>MAny are the opinions, and diſputes, and too curious alſo the diſquiſitions, touching the place, and nature, matter, manner, and duration of <hi>the pains of Hell:</hi> But it would be more Chriſtian prudence ſtrictly to ſearch and find out thoſe crooked, deceitful and polluted paths which lead to that diſmal place of torments, that we may decline and avoid them.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſurely better by much not to feel by woful experience the miſeries of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, than exactly to know, and accurately to diſcourſe of them. And may this be ever my ſtudy, bleſſed Lord, my continual care, and fear, and conſtant endeavour not in the leaſt particular to ſin againſt thee: for thy wrath and indignation which reſteth upon ſinners, is a fierce wrath, and a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, 'tis not in the power of frail man to ſuſtain the fury of it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:56040:33"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. I. <hi>Of the Pain of Loſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS there are two general parts of every ſin in this life committed: 1. An a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from the Creator: 2. A converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Creature. So there are two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral kinds of puniſhment for Sin in the Life to come: 1. The Puniſhment of Loſs: 2. The Pain of Senſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt, and 'tis eſteemed by many holy Fathers the greateſt of Hell-Torments, is that which is call'd by Divines, <hi>The Pain of Loſs,</hi> whereunto the wicked of the world are ſentenced in theſe ſeveral expreſſions:
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.30.41. Luke 13.27. <hi>S. Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Take him away — Caſt him out — I know you not — depart from me ye curſed—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">"The Pains of Senſe in Hell, are intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable (ſaith <hi>Chryſ.</hi>) yet for a man to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a thouſand Hells is leſs irkſome, than to be baniſh'd from Heaven, to be driven from the preſence of God, to be exil'd out of the Regions of Light and Joy, to be rejected of the Lord, and to hear from him, <hi>I know you not — Depart from me—</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Loſs of Heaven muſt needs be the greateſt of Evils, becauſe 'tis the Loſs of the greateſt and moſt perfect good, and of all that is truly good.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:56040:33"/>
               <p>To loſe the good things we do now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in the world, may be recompenced with advantage by the gain of Heaven; but to loſe Heaven it ſelf, to forfeit the right and title we once had happily obtained to be inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Kingdom of Heaven, is a Loſs irreparable; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. Serm. Aug. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chir. ad Laurent. c.</hi> 112.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">"Nothing can compenſate, nothing can equal, nothing to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to this Loſs, 'tis Hell enough it ſelf if there were no other.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In this life the moſt wiſe and holy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not throughly the fulneſs of Heavenly joys, and ſo cannot be ſenſible of the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Loſs: but in the next life our eyes ſhall be opened, and the veil upon our hearts removed, and then ſhall the ungodly ſee, to their unſpeakable grief and anguiſh of ſpirit the vaſt difference betwixt the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fading pleaſures of the right hand of God, and the empty tranſitory pleaſures of ſin; betwixt that fulneſs of joy in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and the deplorable ſorrow of its loſs and abſence.</p>
               <p>It is very probable, that this Torment of Hell is meant by <hi>the Worm that dieth not:</hi> For nothing can more corrode, and eat ſo deeply even into the inmoſt receſſes of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Souls, as to ſee and conſider for what poor beggarly, trifling things of the Earth here below they have loſt thoſe bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Joys and raviſhing Felicities of Heaven above, when they ſhall remember how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany were their ſinful pleaſures, but never to be ended their pains: Then ſhall they curſe their Parents that begat, and the womb that bare them, and the paps they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56040:34"/>ſucked; ſo terrible ſhall be the Torment of this never dying, ever-gnawing Worm, that they ſhall curſe themſelves that they do ſtill live, yea and curſe God himſelf, who is bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have called but ye have refuſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 1.24. Ezek. 33.11. Mat. 11.28. Joh. 6.37, 44, 56.</note> ſaith the Lord: called ſaying, <hi>Turn ye, turn ye unto me with all your heart—Come unto me all ye that are weary—</hi>But we vain men ſlight and neglect, nay too many contemn ſuch gracious invitations: they are not affected or delighted with the preſence of God, or if they come to his houſe, and approach his preſence there, 'tis not either with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Devotion, and external Reverence, 'tis not with ſuch pure hearts and clean hands, as becomes the preſence of ſo great and glorious, ſo holy and pure a Majeſty: and is it not then moſt juſt and equal, that all ſuch irreligious, irreverent and profane perſons be baniſh'd the bliſsful preſence of God for ever?</p>
               <p>And ſo hath the Lord threatned, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65.12. — <hi>Becauſe when I called ye did not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; when I ſpake ye did not hear, but did evil — Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, my ſervants ſhall eat, but ye ſhall be hungry; my ſervants ſhall drink, but ye ſhall be thirſty; my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: Behold, my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall houl for vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatever therefore be the guiſe of the multitude, to walk every one after the luſts of their own hearts, and to follow their own imaginations in the contempt of the Lord's
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56040:34"/>admonitions and commands,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>yet as for me</hi> whilſt I have life and liberty <hi>I will come into thy houſe, even upon the multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and in thy fear will I worſhip towards thy holy Temple</hi>—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My heart hath talked of thee</hi> and of this gracious command of thine.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.9,</note> 
                  <hi>Seek ye my face—Thy face, Lord, will I ſeek:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> O hide not thou thy face from me</hi> under the cloud of my ſins and the thick cloud of my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>nor caſt away thy ſervant in diſpleaſure:</hi> but vouchſafe that my approaches to thy divine Majeſty may be ſo frequent and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and with ſuch Humility, Reverence and Devotion performed, that my perſon and my ſervices may in this life be accepted before thee, that I hear not at the laſt day that diſmal doom of the wicked, <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed</hi>—</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. II. <hi>Of the Darkneſs of Hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO be baniſhed the preſence of God, who is the Fountain of Light is to be involved in the terrors of Darkneſs:
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.13. <hi>Ca.</hi> 25.30. Job 10.21, 22.</note> and therefore after, <hi>Take him away,</hi> it follows, <hi>caſt him into outer darkneſs:</hi> And ſo is the place of Hell deſcribed: <hi>A land of darkneſs and of the ſhadow of death, a land of darkneſs as darkneſs it ſelf, and of the ſhadow of death, without any order, and where light is as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:56040:35"/>And this muſt needs be ſo, becauſe Hell is fartheſt remote from Heaven the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Light, being ſeated (as 'tis generally believed) in the centre of the earth, where neither Sun, Moon nor Stars diſplay the leaſt ray or glimmering of their Light, and where not the leaſt beam of the divine Mercy ſhall ever appear.</p>
               <p>There is Fire indeed in Hell, but ſuch a Fire as burns without ſhining, a Fire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light, not unlike whereunto is the Fire of blind Zeal,
<note place="margin">Jam. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the tongue whereof ſetteth on fire the courſe of nature, and is ſet on fire of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the light which the ſulphurous Fire of Hell affords, ſerves only to diſcover the ghaſtly ſight of infernal Fiends, reviling, ſcourging, tormenting the damned without mercy, without intermiſſion: and there perhaps may the wicked ſee ſome of their friends, and acquaintance, and of their companions in their ſins involv'd with them in the ſame puniſhment, which are ſights ſo dreadful as ſhall augment their Torments.</p>
               <p>Here is darkneſs then, and no darkneſs: ſuch darkneſs, as ſhall hide from the eyes whatever is pleaſant and deſirable: and yet no darkneſs to hide from the diſmal ſight whatever is vexatious, and adds the greater anguiſh to the aking heart.</p>
               <p>This diſmal darkneſs of Hell is call'd <hi>The outward darkneſs,</hi> reſpecting the <hi>inward darkneſs</hi> of humane Souls, and thoſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold deeds of darkneſs which iſſue from the one, and run head-long to the other.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:56040:35"/>
               <p>If then thou haſt followed the luſts of thine own <hi>darkned</hi> heart, and obeyed the ſuggeſtions of Satan <hi>the Prince of darkneſs,</hi> if thou haſt loved and acted the <hi>works of darkneſs</hi> (of ſinfulneſs and error) more than the ſacred acts and influences of Grace and Truth, it is moſt juſt that thy portion be with <hi>blackneſs of darkneſs</hi> for ever.
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Vouchſafe, bleſſed Lord of light and life, vouchſafe to diſplay the ſacred beams of thy Celeſtial light into my darkned Soul, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and diſſipate thence all the black ſtain and guilt of ſin contracted by my daily back-ſlidings from thee, all thoſe clouds of ignorance and error, which darken my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, all thoſe noiſom luſts of the world and of the fleſh which inceſſantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and infect my Soul, that I paſs not from theſe <hi>inward</hi> to that <hi>outward darkneſs where is weeping and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. III. <hi>Of the Fire of Hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF all the Torments invented and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the malice of men or devils, that by Fire is the moſt fierce and frightful: how does it amaze the minds of men, when they ſee it flaming in their houſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming their habitations and eſtates? and yet <hi>the Fire of Hell</hi> is far more dreadful and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56040:36"/>tormenting, as differing from our ordinary fire eſpecially in three reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our fire feeds only upon groſs and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal ſubſtances, but <hi>Hell fire</hi> feeds upon ſpirits and damned ſouls; and 'tis therefore as much more fierce and piercing than our fire, as a ſpirit is more quick and active, than a groſs heavy body.</p>
               <p>Be not deceived (O my Soul) with any fond conceits of vain men, that this fire is only metaphorical, or fantaſtical, allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or poetical, becauſe 'tis prepared for the Devil and his Angels, who are ſpirits, and not liable to viſible flames: But the word of God which cannot lie, and many undeniable reaſons by the learned deduced thence,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.12. cap. 13.42. cap. 25.41. Mark 9.43, 47.</note> do confirm it to be a real, yea a material fire, but more ſpiritual and refined, and ſo more eating, piercing and tormenting than the fire which burns upon our hearths.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our fire doth alway burn and torment after the ſame manner; but Hell-fire being the inſtrument of divine Juſtice, doth more or leſs rage and afflict, according as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons condemned thereunto have been more or leſs guilty.</p>
               <p>And 'tis obſervable, that the ſinful Souls doomed to theſe flames are repreſented by our Lord unto thoſe Tares that are bound in bundles to be burnt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.30. deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all kind of ſinners to be puniſhed with them that are of their own rank and quality: <hi>e.g.</hi> The proud with the proud: The drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard with his good fellow: The adulterer with the unclean; and ſo in all others, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the enormities of their lives, ſhall be their ſuſterings after death.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:56040:36"/>
               <p>And although in this life 'tis ſome miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of ſorrow to have companions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of the ſame quality; yet in Hell 'tis far otherwiſe; for there the more ſinners with their ſins, the more fuel is added to that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal fire: So that when I conſider, all the ſins that have been committed againſt the Majeſty of Heaven ſince the beginning of the world to the end thereof, are as ſo many faggots to feed the fire of Hell; I cannot but tremble at the greatneſs of its force and fury; and carefully avoid the ſociety of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this life, that I ſuffer not with them to the encreaſe of our mutual torments in the other world.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our fire may be quenched,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.12. Iſa. 66. ult. Iſa. 30. ult.</note> nay 'twill quench it ſelf when its fuel is waſted: but the fire of Hell is <hi>unquenchable:</hi> becauſe Firſt, The breath of the everlaſting God, like a ſtream of Brimſtone doth enkindle it. Secondly, The fuel that feeds this fire ſhall never be conſumed, <hi>viz.</hi> Immaterial, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Beings, of whom being tormented in theſe flames 'tis affirmed,
<note place="margin">Rev. 9.6.</note> that <hi>they ſhall ſeek death, and ſhall not find it, they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to die, but death ſhall fly from them.</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretches! whilſt they had time and leiſure to ſeek life, they neglected it; nay, it is too common,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ut cujus vita mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua fuit in culpa, illic mors vivat in poena.</hi> Greg.</note> that when life in Chriſt is offered unto many in the bleſſed food of their Souls, they ſlight and contemn it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis moſt juſt (as the Father obſerves) that <hi>they whoſe life in this world was no other than a death in ſin, their death hereafter ſhould be a life in puniſhment for ſin everlaſtingly.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:56040:37"/>
               <p>But as to the unquenchable fire of Hell, Remember (O my Soul) that there is now a fire within thee, the which if it be not quencht in this life, will bring thee to fire unquenchable in the other world: and this is the rank and fulſom fire of Concupiſcence. Thy carnal luſts, and thy worldly luſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now followed and fulfilled, are the fuel that feeds that diſmal fire of the Infernal Lake: and <hi>the worm alſo that never dieth,</hi> is bred of the ſame corruption, even in the dunghil luſts of the heart, actuated by the hot ſuggeſtions of Satan.</p>
               <p>And as the fire of Concupiſcence doth now more or leſs rage in thy heart, ſo as to follow the ſway thereof; ſo ſhall the fire of Hell be, more or leſs raging hereafter, if theſe luſts do not die within thee, before the death of nature ſeize thee.</p>
               <p>Take then the advice of the Wiſe <hi>Syraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des:
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.17.</note> Humble thy ſelf greatly, for the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the wicked is fire and worms.</hi> And of S.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul: Mortifie therefore your members that are upon earth, fornication, uncleanneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affection, evil concupiſcence, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs which is Idolatry—For which things ſake, the wrath of God cometh upon the children of diſobedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by the merits and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thy Circumciſion I humbly beg the true Circumciſion of the Spirit: and by the virtue of thy Crucifixion ſtrengthen me to crucifie the fleſh with the affections and luſts, leſt any of thoſe exorbitant fires being not opportunely quenched, involve
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56040:37"/>me in thoſe flames of Hell which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. IV. <hi>Of the extent of Hell-Pains.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. mor.</note>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">WHen I conſider righteous <hi>Job</hi> on the Dunghil, the holy <hi>Baptiſt</hi> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring in the Wilderneſs, S. <hi>James</hi> behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, S. <hi>Peter</hi> crucified, the Torments and Deaths of innumerable Martyrs, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Afflictions of the holy and elect people of God; I cannot but conſider, and know aſſuredly that very great and many ſhall be the Torments of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the world to come: ſince God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth thoſe whom he dearly loves to be ſo much afflicted in this life.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Pains of Hell in the extent of them do herein differ from all preſent bodily pains: that theſe are partial only in ſome particular parts, joynts, and members of the body, whilſt other parts are free from pain: But in Hell the whole man in all the Senſes internal and external, in all the parts of his body and powers of his ſoul, yea the moſt ſpiritual faculties ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone, rage and deſpite, grief and anguiſh, miſery and malediction. For the pains of Hell are a concourſe of all
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56040:38"/>kinds of pain, of all at the ſame time, and of all of them for ever.</p>
               <p>The Taſte ſhall be puniſhed with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Appetite with hunger, and the Tongue with thirſt, the Sight with horror, the Hearing with aſtoniſhment, the Smell with ſtench, the Heart with anguiſh, the Imagination with fear, the Reaſon with madneſs, the Judgment with confuſion, and in the very Bowels fire unquenchable.</p>
               <p>And this is moſt juſt, that as the wicked have employed all the powers and parts both of Soul and Body, as weapons of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs unto ſin; ſo ſhould their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be in all their Senſes, Members, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties— that as each hath tranſgreſt by ſinful Pleaſure, and inordinate Delight, ſo each ſhould have its peculiar afflicting Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>There is no ſin unrepented in this life, but ſhall have its proper peculiar torment in Hell: There the proud ſhall be filled with confuſion: The ſlothful ſhall be pricked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with burning goads: The covetous ſhall be pinched with penury: The glutton and the drunkard ſhall be pined with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual hunger and thirſt: The envious ſhall howl like mad dogs for rage and grief: The luxurious and lovers of Pleaſures more than lovers of God, ſhall wallow in burning pitch, and ſtinking brimſtone: And in a word, in whatſoever thing a man hath in this life offended, in the ſame ſhall he be tormented, if not by a true and timely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance prevented. And this the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56040:38"/>
                  <hi>Dives</hi> felt, when he wanted a drop of cold water to cool his Tongue in Hell, who whilſt upon earth had fared ſumptuouſly every day.</p>
               <p>'Tis undoubtedly true, that all perſons condemned to the flames of the nether Hell are not equally tormented therein: for though the fire of Hell be one and the ſame, yet it torments not all after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor in the ſame degree of torture: but every man ſhall therein more or leſs feel the ſmart of its fury, as by the nature, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and frequency of his ſin, he hath leſs or more deſerved the ſame:
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> for <hi>ſhall not the Judge of all the world do right?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The more high, peremptory and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, as alſo the leſs obſtinate and impenient ſinner ſhall both ſuffer under the torment of the ſame fire, but not in the ſame degree of pain and ſuſlering: As under the ſame heat of the Sun upon Earth all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not alike ſcorched, but ſome are more, ſome leſs ſenſible of its darting beams, according to their ſeveral conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions: So in the fire of Hell, the degree of its burning ſhall not be alike in all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what here the diverſity of bodies, there the diverſity of ſins ſhall effect: So that though all be tormented with the like flames, yet not every one in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and degree of torment. <hi>Gregor.</hi> But alas the loweſt degree of ſuffering in that place of horror is puniſhment enough, if ſeriouſly conſidered, to afright the ſinner from all the errors of his ways.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:56040:39"/>
               <p>There be many who now think this or that to be ſevere commands, <hi>Love your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies—Deny thy Self, Faſt, and Watch, and Pray— Take up thy Croſs</hi>— but ſurely 'twill be much more hard and bitter to hear,
<note place="margin">Tho à Kemp.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire</hi>—</p>
               <p>There was an Hermite call'd <hi>Olympius,</hi> who had a Cell near the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> where he was conſtantly plagued both with exceſſive heat, and the bitings of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Flies: who being demanded why he would continue there to endure ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual vexations: Anſwered, I ſuffer pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently the bitings of theſe Flies, that I may eſcape the diſmal bitings of that Worm that dieth not: And this great heat I endure, that I may eſcape the flames of Hell, which are intolerable and everlaſting, and theſe Heats but for a moment. <hi>Prat. Spir. c.</hi> 141.</p>
               <p>O let not then the ſevereſt commands of the Goſpel, nor the difficulties and labours of Repentance ſtartle and afright thee: let not the breach or neglect thereof, ſeem a light and a ſmall thing unto thee; but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that to endure the pains of Hell but one hour, is more exceeding painful and aſſlicting, than a thouſand years of the moſt ſtrict and ſevere auſterities in Faſting, and Sackcloth and Aſhes.</p>
               <p>Remember the Worm that dieth not: The Fire that is not quenched: The inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſociety of tormenting Devils: The horrid howlings of damned Souls: The everlaſting baniſhment from the preſence of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56040:39"/>God, and from the Regions of light: The inſufferable ſtench, horror, and ſtifling fumes: The Eternal hunger and thirſt, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and woe; and ſurely if theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances will not move thee to imbrace the ſtricteſt commands of thy bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, thy heart is hard indeed, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than the nether Milſtone. 'Twas other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with the <hi>Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.120.</note> my fleſh trembleth for fear of thee; and I am afraid of thy judgments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I humbly beg I may be here, even here in this life puniſh'd for my ſins, but ſpare, O ſpare me in the life to come, and from thoſe intolerable pains of the nether Hell, good Lord deliver me, through <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. V. <hi>Of the Bonds and Chains of Hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RIghteous art thou, O Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.137.</note> and upright are thy Judgments:</hi> 'Tis a juſtice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the juſt judge of the World, that the Licentious and Profane, who in this life would not be <hi>bound up</hi> nor reſtrained from following and fulfilling their exorbitant luſts, but have <hi>walked</hi> in the counſel of the ungodly, and <hi>ſtood</hi> in the way of ſinners; that they who <hi>bound up</hi> their hands from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the works of God's Commandments, and <hi>bound up</hi> their feet from walking in the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56040:40"/>paths of his moſt holy Laws; that they whoſe ſins are <hi>bound</hi> upon theirs Souls, and not looſed by true Repentance through Faith in the Bloud of Chriſt: 'tis juſt, I ſay, that ſuch ſhould incurr this ſad and diſmal Sentence,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Bind him hand and foot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the <hi>feet</hi> in holy Writ is frequently meant our affections whereby our Souls do move, as our bodies do by our feet: And by our hands our actions are meant: ſo that by the binding of both in Hell is intimated, that it ſhall not there be poſſible, either to act, or ſo much as affect what is good, and conducible to our redemption thence.</p>
               <p>To be bound to one place, though in Silken Cords, or Chains of Gold, though 'twere on a Bed of Roſes, or the ſweeteſt Perfumes, to be ſo tied as not to be able to ſtir hand or foot, is a very great puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the free, active and ſtirring ſoul of Man: How much more then a ſorer pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is it, to be bound in fiery Chains, eating through the fleſh into the very Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, nay through all the moſt hidden and deepeſt receſſes of the Soul, and be forced to lie down in a Bed of Flames, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not to be able to ſtir either <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>foot,</hi> not to move or change from ſide to ſide for the leaſt eaſe or mitigation of Torment?</p>
               <p>For the binding of the feet implies there's no eſcaping, no flying from the place of Torment; and the binding of the hands, that there's no fence againſt the tormenting Fiends; that there's no way to be gone, no work to be done to mitigate in the leaſt their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56040:40"/>inſupportable ſufferings: 'Tis therefore one great reaſon of God's forbearance with fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this life to bring them to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, becauſe there's no poſſibility by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to abate the ſorrows of impenitent ſinners in the life to come.</p>
               <p>He muſt have a heart of Stone, or rather of Flint the hardeſt of Stones, who in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his ſins is not greatly terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and humbled in the very thought and apprehenſion of theſe fiery tormenting <hi>Chains of Hell.</hi> And ſuch a hardneſs of heart is contracted by a long continued cuſtom in any ſinful courſe: And every ſin unrepented is juſtly puniſhed. 1. By being inſenſible of ſin; and 2. without the fear or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of future Judgments, which makes that vaſt difference betwixt the wiſe man and the fool: <hi>The wiſe man feareth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from evil, but the fool rageth and is confident,</hi> Prov. 14.16.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> whoſe innocent tender hands were rudely ſeized and bound with Cords of injuſtice and violence, vouchſafe to looſe all the Bonds and Chains of my Sins, wherewith both my hands and feet, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and actions are infettered and infeſted; and grant that the wounds they have made in my Soul being waſhed with my Tears, may be healed by the Soveraign Balſam which from thy Wounds and Stripes and Bonds does flow:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 25.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Pluck my feet out of the Net</hi> of every temptation to ſinfulneſs and error,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.48.</note> and <hi>let my hands be continually lift up unto thy Commandments to do them,</hi> that I
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56040:41"/>be not liable to be bound by any of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of vengeance in the fiery Chains of the nether Hell, where is weeping and wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing—</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. VI. <hi>Of the Laments of Hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THere ſhall be weeping,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.30.</note> and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> They ſhall deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly weep in Hell, whoſe eyes upon earth have been <hi>full of Adultery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14.</note> Laſciviouſneſs and greedineſs of the Creature: whoſe <hi>eyes have been ſet upon their covetouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 13.30.</note> and their eye-lids lifted up with ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others: who have been guilty of any of theſe, or of any other ſinful pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and have not wept and bewailed the ſame with the tears of Repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wo unto you that laugh now</hi> in your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful pleaſures,
<note place="margin">Luk. 6.25.</note> 
                  <hi>for ye ſhall mourn and weep</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here or hereafter: And 'tis ſad and ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh to put off this neceſſity of weeping to the other world, where the Tears of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſad Repentance ſhall avail no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>And this is all the water that Hell affords,
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.24.</note> not a drop to cool the tongue tormented in thoſe ſcorching Flames, only thoſe drieſly Tears, which the violence of her Torments do extort, which being ſalt and briniſh, and ſpent in vain, ſhall the more encreaſe the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56040:41"/>bitterneſs and augment the miſeries of the condemned ſinner.</p>
               <p>Weeping in this life, as 'tis a ſign, ſo 'tis ſome eaſe to the inward ſorrow of the Soul, which outwardly evaporates it ſelf by Tears: But 'tis not thus with the weepings in Hell; there no Tears, no Sighs, not the ſaddeſt Lamentations can mitigate in the leaſt the ſorrows of the Soul; becauſe there is nothing but what doth torment, without any intermixture of eaſe, or allay: which is manifeſt from the conjunction of <hi>weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth,</hi> to intimate there is not ſuch a Lamentation as gives eaſe to the Soul, but rather embitters the ſame even to rage and madneſs, and dire execrations of it ſelf, and of all its inſtruments and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in her ſins, accompanied with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous revilings of the juſtice of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O that now my head were waters,
<note place="margin">Jer. 9.1.</note> and mine eyes a fountain of tears,</hi> by weeping here, to prevent the weeping in Hell hereafter, now to bewail my ſins, that I ſorrow not when 'tis too late, where weeping and wailing ſhall not aſſwage but augment my ſorrows.</p>
               <p>Lament, O ſinner, and <hi>gnaſh thy teeth</hi> through a holy indignation, to be ſo fooliſh and mad, as for a little ſinful pleaſure, or dirty delight, to run the hazard of being obnoxious to never-ending pains and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.4.</note> both for their own ſins, and for the ſins of others through the fear of Hell, and deſire of Heaven; <hi>for they ſhall be comforted,</hi> their ſcars prevented, their deſires obtained.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:56040:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A broken and a contrite heart,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 51.17.</note> O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe:</hi> A heart broken with godly ſorrow for ſin, and venting it ſelf in Tears with Prayers, Humiliations and Confeſſions mixt with Faith in the Bloud of my dear Redeemer. Thus Lord, thus I humbly beg to be delivered from thy wrath, and from the deplorable wailings of a ſad eternity. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. VII. <hi>Of the Perpetuity of Hell-Torments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Perpetuity of Hell-Torments is in the thought thereof a Torment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable: for in every inſtant of the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the Damned, they ſuffer all the Torments of thoſe infinite thouſands of years to come, the continuance whereof is not meaſured by Time, but by the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Abyſs of Eternity, and the immutability of Divine Juſtice: and what is time to eternity? <hi>Behold as a drop of water is to the ſea,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 18.10.</note> and a gravel-ſtone in compariſon of the ſand: ſo are a thouſand years to the days of eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this life <hi>fear hath torment:</hi> but torment hath no fear, but hope rather of releaſe, and delivery, but in Hell the Damned both
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56040:42"/>fear what they ſuffer, and alſo ſuffer what they fear, even the everlaſting duration of their ſufferings:
<note place="margin">Rev. 20.10.</note> 
                  <hi>They that are caſt into the Lake of fire and brimſtone ſhall be tormented day and night for ever, and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Damned in Hell (ſaith holy <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>) ſhall die unto life, and yet ſhall for ever live unto death: For therefore ſhall they live for ever, that they may be the food of death eternal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not they</hi> then <hi>without underſtanding that work wickedneſs?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.4.</note> who being endued with Reaſon, and capable of Counſel, who knowing the ſhortneſs of this life, and the uncertainty of the ſame, and withal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the everlaſting duration of the life to come, do nevertheleſs bend all their thoughts and endeavours upon what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns this preſent temporary Being, even to the great hazard of being obnoxious to the Pains and Torments of a ſad Eternity: ſuch madneſs in the hearts of men can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be throughly bewail'd even with Tears of Bloud.</p>
               <p>Wo to them who now do laugh at what ſhall be hereafter moſt ſadly bewailed: and wo to them who ſhall feel by ſad experience what they now either believe not, or but ſlightly regard it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 3.7.</note> That there is a wrath to come every Chriſtian believes, and 'tis a fierce wrath and a terrible,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.8, 9.</note> even <hi>indignation and wrath, tribulation and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man that doth evil,</hi> and hath not repented
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56040:43"/>him of the evil, and of the iniquity he hath done.</p>
               <p>Of the coming of this wrath alſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent warning is given, both by the works and by the word of God, and by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of his Church: but who takes war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning given? <hi>who regards the power of this wrath?</hi> very few regard it; though the leſs it be regarded, the more fierce it will be, <hi>for even thereafter as a man feareth,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 90.11.</note> ſo is thy diſpleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fear thou the Lord,
<note place="margin">Prov. 3.7.</note> O my Soul, <hi>fear the Lord, and depart from evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.7.</note> O Lord, thou alone art to be feared, and who may ſtand in thy ſight, when thou art angry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life,
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.27.</note> to depart from the gates of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fear not them that can kill the body,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.28.</note> but are not able to kill the ſoul: but fear him who is able to deſtroy both ſoul and body in hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us have grace whereby we may ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For our God is a conſuming fire.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:56040:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> LXXXVI. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> PARAPHRASED.</head>
               <head type="sub">Verſe 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BOw down thine ear</hi> to him who now bows down his heart, <hi>and hear me, O Lord,</hi> confeſſing, <hi>for I am poor,</hi> extremely want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the graces of thy Spirit, which ſhould make me rich towards God: I have little or no treaſures laid up in Heaven, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I am in miſery,</hi> liable to the eternal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of Hell: But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſerve thou my ſoul</hi> from that diſmal place of Torments, <hi>for I am holy,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſeparate and devoted to thy Service, though a poor unprofitable ſervant: and upon this account I make bold to call thee <hi>my God,</hi> whom I worſhip and ſerve, and humbly beſeech thee <hi>to ſave thy ſervant who putteth his truſt in thee,</hi> for the riches of grace and ſalvation, wherein</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be merciful unto me, O Lord,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> who art rich in mercy, <hi>for I will call daily upon thee,</hi> that it may pleaſe thee in great mercy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from that miſery, whereunto my poorneſs in grace, but abounding ſins, make me obnoxious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Comfort the ſoul of thy ſervant</hi> that the ſorrows of death overwhelm me not:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <hi>For
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56040:44"/>unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my ſoul,</hi> being hereunto encouraged by thy grace and goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thou,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Lord, art good,</hi> even the inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible Fountain of goodneſs, <hi>and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> propitiouſly inclined to hear the ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of thy people, <hi>and of great mercy</hi> againſt the greatneſs of iniquity, <hi>unto all them that call upon thee,</hi> even to all that call upon thee faithfully, depending upon thee alone for help, and ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Give ear,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> to my prayer,</hi> not ſlightly hearing the ſound of my words, but <hi>ponder the voice of my humble deſires:</hi> the intenſe deſires of my humbled ſoul, I humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the time of my trouble,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> and that's the whole time of my Pilgrimage here upon earth, <hi>I will call upon thee</hi> for protection and deliverance, whereof I will never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair: <hi>for thou heareſt me,</hi> if my Prayer be pure and humble: and therefore will I call upon thee as long as I live.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Among the Gods</hi> that be either falſly ſo called,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> or be ſo called by participation of divine Power as the Angels in Heaven, and Kings of the Earth, <hi>there is none like unto thee, O Lord,</hi> either for Power or Wiſdom: <hi>there is none that can do as thou doſt:</hi> thy Works do far exceed the Power of any created Beings to do the like: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in fulneſs of time,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All nations whom thou haſt made,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> ſhall no longer make Gods unto themſelves, but <hi>ſhall come and worſhip thee, O Lord,</hi> the Maker of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:56040:44"/>all Men, and of all Things, and being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Members of thy holy Catholick Church <hi>ſhall glorifie thy Name,</hi> both with heart and voice, and by the good Works of their Obedience to the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thou art great,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> which all thy Works declare, and <hi>doſt wondrous things,</hi> not to be apprehended but admired, and 'tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all the parts of the World confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that <hi>thou art God alone,</hi> all others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either falſly or feignedly called Gods: And that I may accordingly worſhip thee aright,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teach me thy way, O Lord,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> that I neither miſtake the right way, nor ſtumble and fall therein, but ſtedfaſtly and conſtantly <hi>walk in thy truth:</hi> and this Way and this Truth is my bleſſed Redeemer, who by his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Example, Doings and Sufferings, Life and Death, is the way that leads to Life Eternal: <hi>O knit my heart unto thee,</hi> by the indiſſoluble bonds of a true Faith, firm Hope, fervent Charity: <hi>that I may fear thy Name,</hi> ſo as that I neither dare to ſin againſt thee, nor too much preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will thank thee, O Lord my God,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> as from whom both my whole Self, and all the little good that is mine does proceed, <hi>with all my heart,</hi> as being hereunto excited by the fear and love of thy Name: <hi>and I will praiſe thy Name for evermore:</hi> And there is very great reaſon I ſhould do ſo;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For great is thy mercy toward me,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> not only manifeſted in all the good things I do enjoy,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:56040:45"/>but in my deliverance from manifold evils, and eſpecially from the greateſt of evils: <hi>for thou haſt delivered my ſoul from the nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hell,</hi> in the broad way that leads there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I have a long time walked, and 'tis of thy great mercy, that I have not long ſince been hurled headlong to that diſmal place of Torments: And ſtill I have great cauſe to complain,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> the proud are riſen againſt me,</hi> proud Lucifer and his infernal Fiends, <hi>and the congregation of naughty men have ſought after my ſoul:</hi> the wicked of the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire with the Devil and his Angels by their ſinful ſuggeſtions to ſubvert the innocence of my Soul, to have her portion with them in the neithermoſt Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But thou,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> O Lord, art full of compaſſion,</hi> eſpecially to all them who chuſe rather to ſuffer than to do what is offenſive to thy Majeſty, <hi>and mercy,</hi> in pardoning the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the truly penitent, <hi>long-ſuffering,</hi> not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance, <hi>plenteous in goodneſs,</hi> abounding in thy bleſſings, <hi>and truth</hi> both in performing thy promiſes of mercy to the penitent, and in rendring to every man according to his works.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O turn thee then unto me,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> who by my ſins have juſtly provoked thee to turn away thy face from me; <hi>and have mercy upon me,</hi> a miſerable ſinner: and that I may no more offend thee, <hi>give thy ſtrength unto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> even ghoſtly ſtrength and fortitude, manfully to reſiſt the Devil, and all his nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:56040:45"/>troops of ſenſual and worldly luſts; in all whoſe aſſaults vouchſafe to <hi>help the ſon of thine handmaid,</hi> that I may overcome all their temptations unto evil, and carefully keep my vow and promiſe made when I was firſt admitted to be a Son of thy handmaid the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shew ſome token upon me for good,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> let ſome ſign of thy favour towards me appear, <hi>that they who hate me,</hi> my ghoſtly enemies, <hi>may ſee it and be aſhamed,</hi> when they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all their conſpiracies and aſſaults a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Soul defeated by the aſſiſtance of thy divine Grace: <hi>becauſe thou, Lord, haſt holpen me and comforted me:</hi> thy help to overcome when I am tempted unto ſin, is a great comfort to my Soul, for I have hereupon a good ground of hope, that thou wilt deliver my Soul from the nethermoſt Hell: <hi>and that being raiſed up from the gates of Death, I may ſhew all thy praiſes within the ports of the Daughter of Sion,</hi> Saying,
<q>
                     <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:56040:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> LXXXVIII. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> PARAPHRASED.</head>
               <head type="sub">Verſe 1.</head>
               <p>O <hi>Lord God of my ſalvation,</hi> my Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Spiritual, Temporal and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation is from thee, and therefore <hi>I have cryed day and night</hi> at all times and ſeaſons, and in all conditions proſperous and adverſe <hi>before thee,</hi> as unto whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone the inmoſt intimate deſires of my ſoul are naked and open: <hi>O let my prayer enter into thy preſence,</hi> be received and accepted by thee: <hi>incline thine ear unto my calling,</hi> ſo graciouſly hear as to grant my humble requeſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My ſoul is full of trouble,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which being the conſequent of Sin, is the forerunner of Death, <hi>and my life draweth nigh unto hell,</hi> which openeth wide her mouth to ſwallow down ſuch polluted Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am counted as one of them that go down to the Pit,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> look'd upon as a dead man and a caſt-away: <hi>and I have been even as a man that hath no ſtrength,</hi> which is derived from the Lord of life, to eſcape the ſnares and terrors of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Free among the dead,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> not likely to be freed from my troubles, but by death,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:56040:46"/>which puts an end to all the miſeries of this ſinful life: <hi>like unto them that are woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> by the fiery darts of the Devil, <hi>and lie in the grave</hi> of corrupt converſation, which leads to the grave of death the wages of ſin; and whoſoever thus lie there, <hi>are out of remembrance,</hi> both forgotten by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>and alſo are cut away from thy hand,</hi> repuls'd from amongſt thoſe bleſſed Sheep, which ſhall be rank'd on thy right hand in the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt laid me in the loweſt Pit:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I have ſo far incurr'd thy wrathful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, as to be laid in the nethermoſt Hell, which is <hi>a place of darkneſs,</hi> even blackneſs of darkneſs for ever: <hi>and in the deep</hi> Abyſs of inextricable Torments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thine indignation lieth hard upon me,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> whereto I have provoked thee by manifold offences, <hi>and thou haſt vexed me with all thy ſtorms;</hi> thoſe tempeſts of affliction and trouble which diſturb my peace are ſent from thee to ſcowre the ruſt of corruption off my Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt put away mine acquaintance far from me, and made me to be abhorred of them:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The inviſible ſociety of holy Angels, with the prayers and good wiſhes of holy men I enjoyed whilſt I was innocent, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-minded; but now being polluted, they are eſtranged from me, and abhor me in my ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am ſo faſt in priſon,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> that I cannot get forth:</hi> I am ſo enfetter'd in the bonds and chains of my ſins, that without the help
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56040:47"/>of a divine hand I cannot be looſed from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My ſight faileth for very trouble,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> the bright eye of my mind is dimm'd and darkned through the preſſures of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and in this ſad condition, <hi>Lord, I have called upon thee,</hi> as being my only refuge in danger, ſupport in trouble, and ſuccour in all diſtreſs, <hi>I have ſtretched forth my hands unto thee,</hi> by my practice according to my prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doſt thou ſhew wonders among the dead?</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> or ſhall the dead declare thy works of wonder? <hi>or ſhall the dead riſe up and praiſe thee?</hi> They muſt have part in the firſt Reſurrection (which is from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of ſin) who worthily ſhew forth thy praiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall thy loving kindneſs be ſhewed in the grave,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> or thy faithfulneſs in deſtruction?</hi> both in the ſtate of the firſt, and of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death, there is a deep ſilence of thy Goodneſs and of thy Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall thy wondrous works be known in the dark,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> and thy righteouſneſs in the land where all things are forgotten?</hi> Thy righteous and admired deeds are not once mentioned ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the grave of Death, or in the Pit of Hell: in both eſtates there is an utter for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs of all thy Goodneſs and Truth. But that I may be delivered from ſuch a ſad condition,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee have I cried,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> O Lord: and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall my prayer come before thee:</hi> Before I be ſurpriſed by Death, let my prayer for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:56040:47"/>thy prevented and aſſiſting Grace be not rejected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, why abhorreſt thou my ſoul?</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> I am unclean I confeſs, and 'tis but juſt I ſhould be abhorred and forſaken, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withal penitent and humbled; <hi>why hideſt thou thy face from me,</hi> as being ſtill diſpleaſed with me, and deaf to my peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am in miſery,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> and like unto him that is at the point to die:</hi> Death as the wages of ſin dogs me at the heels: <hi>even from my youth up thy terrors have I ſuffered with a troubled mind:</hi> The terrors of my Conſcience for ſin, have been alway accompanied with a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and contrite ſpirit, which thou haſt promiſed not to deſpiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy wrathful diſpleaſure goeth over me:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> The apprehenſion of thy wrath and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure invades, and overflows my ſoul: <hi>and the fear of thee hath undone me:</hi> the fear of thy wrath in the day of Judgment, and of the never-dying Torments of Hell, hath ruin'd all my worldly conſolations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They came round about me daily like water</hi> overflowing all the powers and paſſions of my Soul,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/>
                  <hi>and compaſſed me together on every ſide,</hi> leaving no viſible means of evaſion and peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My lovers and my friends,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> who profeſſed themſelves to be ſuch in my worldly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and amidſt my carnal delights, <hi>haſt thou put away from me,</hi> they are alienated and eſtranged in time of my trouble: <hi>and hid mine acquaintance out of my ſight,</hi> they
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:56040:48"/>will not now ſee me who formerly frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my company.</p>
               <p>And therefore being thus deſolate, and deeply endeangered, <hi>unto thee</hi> as my only hope and refuge, <hi>O Lord God of my Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have cried day and night</hi> continually, for Deliverance and Salvation, that my ſoul may continually bleſs thee and ſay,
<q>
                     <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="heaven" type="meditation">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:56040:48"/>
            <head>THE Fourth general Meditation OF HEAVEN.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <p n="1">1. THE Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful in theſe words of command:
<note place="margin">Gen. 13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Lift up now thine eyes, and look from the place where thou art, Northward and Southward, Eaſtward and Weſtward— For all the Land which thou ſeeſt, to thee will I give it,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> and to thy ſeed for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Celeſtial <hi>Canaan</hi> is herein promiſed unto thee, if a true Son of the Faithful <hi>Abraham:</hi> Lift up then thine eyes, O my Soul, and Contemplate the raviſhing Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of this Land of Promiſe. This is thy Native Country, where thou waſt at firſt Framed by the hands of the Almighty, after His own Image; Why then doſt thou not pant, and breath, and ſigh, and long to be at Home? Why art thou ſo well pleaſed with
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56040:49"/>a ſtrange Land, and delighteſt rather to be a Pilgrim in the Valley of Tears, than a Free Denizon in the Land of Peace? a Foreigner in the city of <hi>Babylon</hi> than a Citizen in the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem? Away, away from Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon,</hi> O my Soul, thy beloved calleth thee <hi>away from the Dens of Lions,
<note place="margin">Can. 4.8. Pſal. 55.6.</note> and the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Leopards. O that I had wings like a Dove, for then would I flee away and be at reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. We read that the Lord brought <hi>Moſes</hi> to the top of mount <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and ſhewed him the promiſed land, where having the wilderneſs behind him, and the happieſt of all lands before him, he repreſents the devout and heavenly minded Soul, who conſidering the manifold troubles in the wilderneſs of this world, and the joys and felicities of the world to come, is highly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed in the contemplation and deſire of the one, to the extream contempt of the other.</p>
               <p>Did I but ſeriouſly conſider the ways of my preſent peace and contentment, I could not but obſerve, that the Commandments of God have ſo much intrinſick ſweetneſs and felicity in them, as to excite the moſt ſimple and ſtubborn Soul to obey them: and yet ſo exceſſive are the ardors of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs and Love, as to engage our obedience by the promiſes of Celeſtial Joys. Unto this immarceſcible Crown of Glory we are Created by God the Father, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by God the Son, and Sanctified by
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56040:49"/>God the Holy Ghoſt in the ſacred Waters of Baptiſm, wherein we are adopted, not only ſons, but heirs of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>What blindneſs then doth ſo much poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the minds of the greateſt part of the ſons of men, that all their deſires and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſhould be ſo wholly taken up with the vain, frail, empty and dying things of the Earth, to the ſlight and neglect of thoſe never fading joys of Heaven?</p>
               <p>The firſt and largeſt ſtep we take to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, is from the ſtate of Sin into the ſtate of Grace; the other, <hi>viz.</hi> from Grace to Glory is a more eaſie and ready paſſage; there being nothing betwixt the one and the other, but a frail mortal life, which taking end, the Soul that is enriched with the ornaments of divine Grace is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately cloathed with the Robes of Glory: and therefore both the one and the other is ſtiled by our Lord <hi>Life Eternal,</hi> John 17.3. <hi>This is Life Eternal, that we might know thee</hi>—</p>
               <p n="3">3. The happineſs of Heaven is the end of all Holineſs upon Earth; and that muſt needs be the greateſt good, which is the end of all that is good, for <hi>the end is more noble than the means.</hi> 'Tis the laſt good we hope for, and ſo the moſt perfect, as being the perfection and accompliſhment of all the good we can imagine or deſire; nay, 'tis a bleſſedneſs beyond our frail imaginations to comprehend: <hi>as it is written, eye hath not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:56040:50"/>ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quod De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus ſe, fide non capitur, ſpe non attingitur, charitate non comprehenditur, deſideria &amp; vota tranſgreditur: acquiri poteſt, aeſtimari non poteſt.</hi> Aug. in 1 Cor. 2.9.</note>.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Raiſe up thy affections (O my Soul) as to be raviſh'd with the love of Heaven, ſo to lament with tears of ſorrow and ſhame thy ſloth and negligence, thy coldneſs and indevotion, thy ſinful ſecurity and earthly mindedneſs, and what obſtructs thy way, and ſlackens thy pace towards this place of joy unſpeakable and glorious.</p>
               <p>O how ſlight and trivial, how inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable are all the moſt ſtrict and rigid labours of Repentance and Mortification, of the moſt profound Piety, and ample Charity, in reſpect of thoſe Celeſtial joys whereunto they lead thee!</p>
               <p>And if it ſhall once pleaſe God through the merits of Chriſt to receive thee into Heaven, thou wilt then think all thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and tears,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Age quod vgis, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra in vinea tua: ego (inquit Dominus) ero merces iva: ſcribe, lege, canta, geme, tace, ora, ſuſtine viriliter contraria: digna eſt his omnibus vita aeterna, &amp; majoribus praeliis.</hi> T.K.</note> ſighs and groans, faſtings and watchings, all thy labours of love both to God and Man, very well ſpent, that they have wafted thee over the troubleſome waves of this worlds vaſt Sea, into the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Eternal peace and felicity.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:56040:50"/>
               <p>Vouchſafe me, O Lord, a good end of my life, a happy paſſport out of this world, and lead me in the ſtreight and even path that leads to thy Kingdom; where that I may at laſt arrive, it ſhall neither be my care nor fear, what, and how great things I ſuffer and undergo in my paſſage thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. II. <hi>Of the place we call Heaven, and firſt, its Greatneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat Empyreal Heaven,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2. Deut. 10.14. 2 Chr. 6.18.</note> which is the ſeat of God and of all his holy Angels and Saints for ever, is called alſo <hi>the Third Heaven,</hi> and <hi>the Higheſt Heaven,</hi> and <hi>the Heaven of Heavens;</hi> and 'tis of all the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Univerſe the moſt ſpacious, large and ample: for it contains all the Heavens and the Earth alſo, even the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within its verge and compaſs.</p>
               <p>Do but conſider the vaſtneſs of the Sun, and of the Moon, with the multitude and magnitude of all the Lights of Heaven, moſt of which are greater, and ſome of them far bigger than the whole body of the Earth: Conſider alſo that beſides the vaſt number of Stars, there are empty ſpaces in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament for as many, nay for many more than as many yet: and then admire with aſtoniſhment the vaſt extent and amplitude
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:56040:51"/>of the Heaven of Heavens, which containeth all theſe, and all that is above, and all that is below all theſe, within its circuit and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Secondly, Its brightneſs and Beauty.</head>
                  <p>The brightneſs of the Sun, the Moon and the Stars do but imperfectly repreſent the Beauty and Brightneſs of Heaven, as 'tis deſcribed,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. <hi>And the City had no need of the Sun, nor of the Moon to ſhine in it, for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof;</hi> which exceeds as much the light of the Sun, as the Suns light tranſcends that of a glimmering Taper.</p>
                  <p>The Air of this Country of Heaven is continually pure and clear, bright and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did; 'tis not capable of any Clouds, Miſts, or Vapours, not liable to any Rains, Storms and Tempeſts, not hick infectious Air offends the Inhabitants of this happy Land; whilſt the wretched Miſcreants of the nether Hell are involved in blackneſs of darkneſs, ſtifled with the ſuffocating fumes of ſulphureous fire, without the leaſt hope of any purer Air wherein to breath for ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Thirdly, Its Tranquillity.</head>
                  <p>All in this City of God is peaceable and quiet, tranquil and ſecure, and free even from the fear of the leaſt diſturbance;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.10.</note> 
                     <hi>no evil comes nigh this dwelling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:56040:51"/>
                  <p>'Tis promiſed by our Lord, <hi>John</hi> 16.22. <hi>Your joy no man taketh from you:</hi> 'Tis alone the joy of Heaven, which cannot be taken away: not by the world which is overcome, and trampled under foot: not by the fleſh, for that is ſo ſpiritualized, and refined, as no more to rebel againſt the dictates of the ſpirit: not by ſin, for here enters nothing that is unclean: not by death, for immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality reigneth here: not by any pain or ſickneſs, for theſe are but the Meſſengers and Forerunners of Death: not by chance or fortune, for Heaven knows no ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Deity: not by Envy, Hatred Malice, Strife, — for all the Inhabitants of Heaven are combined in the ſacred Bonds of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Charity. <hi>And God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes; and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow nor crying; neither ſhall there be any more pain, for the former things are paſſed away,</hi> Rev. 21.4.</p>
                  <p>What the Lord promiſeth to his Church Militant is fulfilled in his Church Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 147.13,</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord hath made faſt the bars of thy gates:</hi> they are inexpugnable by any, by the utmoſt force and fury of all the Spirits and Powers of Darkneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord maketh peace in thy borders:</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Bleſſed peace dwells here without the leaſt fear or danger of interruption: For the grand Enemy of Peace is hence caſt down, <hi>fallen like lightning from Heaven,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 10.18.</note> there's no room here for that Author of all diviſion, nor yet for any of his inſtruments,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 68.30.</note> 
                     <hi>The people that delight in war:</hi> 'Tis the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:56040:52"/>of Peace-makers,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.9.</note> and of the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able minded, and of ſuch only as live in Peace upon Earth.</p>
                  <p>And O that it might pleaſe the God of Peace to allay that rancour, to depreſs that tumour, to aſſwage that itch of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which now ſo much diſturbs the peace of his Church upon Earth, and obſtructs the way to this heavenly <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the City of Peace:
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Follow peace with all men, and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O God the Athour of peace and lover of concord, in knowledge of whom ſtandeth our Eternal life, whoſe ſervice is perfect freedom; defend us thy humble ſervants in all the aſſaults of our Enemies, that would diſturb our peace: that we ſurely truſting in thy defence, may not fear the power of any adverſaries, through the might of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt—</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. III. <hi>Of the good things of Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1. HONOUR.</head>
                  <p>HOnour in Heaven is not that which ſwells with vain-glory, and is puft up with the infectious breath of Flattery, and the praiſe of men,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.44.</note> 
                     <hi>but the honour that cometh from God only.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:56040:52"/>
                  <p>Honour is the reward of vertue, and he who is the donor of vertue and obedience has promiſed to honour the obedient and vertuous, ſaying, <hi>If any man ſerve me,
<note place="margin">Joh. 12.26.</note> him will my Father honour:</hi> What, and how great this honour is we read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.31.
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.31.</note> 
                     <hi>To him that overcometh will I give to ſit with me in my Throne: even as I have overcome, and am ſet down with my Father in his Throne:</hi> There cannot be ſurely an higher Honour than this, to be exalted by the right hand of the moſt High, and placed in the ſame Throne with the <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords:</hi> O what Hymns of divine Praiſe, what applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and exultations, what ſhouts of joy ſhall ſound through the whole Court of Heaven, when <hi>thus it ſhall be done to the man whom the King delighteth to honour.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſth. 6.11.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2. POWER.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Honour</hi> without <hi>Power</hi> is but a titular, empty, airy happineſs: And the Saints ſhall have all power of what they will, as God hath of what he wills: For as God can do what he will by himſelf, ſo can they do what they will by him: For as they will nothing but what the Lord wills; ſo the Lord wills nothing but what they will have; 'tis not poſſible, but that they have Power to do whatever they will; ſo <hi>Aug. Manual. c.</hi> 35. The <hi>Power</hi> of the Saints in Heaven is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Lord of all power, ſaying of the <hi>faithful and wiſe ſervant,
<note place="margin">Matt. 24.45, 46.</note> he will make him ruler of all his goods:</hi> implying a power given
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:56040:53"/>to his Saints, not only over all that is called good upon earth, but alſo over all the joys of Heaven, which are an aggregation of all that is good. 'Tis promiſed to him that overcometh, that he ſhall inherit all things; for being the Sons of God, they are alſo heirs of God, and joynt heirs with Chriſt, partakers of all power with him both in Heaven and Earth.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cloſſ. ord. in loc.</hi> Rev. 21.7.</note> 
                     <hi>He that overcometh ſhall inherit all things:</hi> wherein are implicitely promiſed,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3. RICHES.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The Riches</hi> of Heaven, are not ſuch corruptible things as Silver and Gold, gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Attire, delicious Fare, large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes, fair Habitations — but without any ſuch frail deceitful pelf there ſhall be <hi>abundance of peace,
<note place="margin">Pſ 72.7. 2 Cor. 4.17. 2 Cor. 15.28.</note> a fulneſs of perfection and felicity, an exceeding and eternal weight of glory:</hi> and in a word; in Heaven <hi>God ſhall be all in all:</hi> He who is the Fountain and Well-ſpring of all good gifts and graces up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, will be himſelf the Reward and Crown thereof in Heaven; than the which there can be nothing more high and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, nothing more great and powerful, nothing more rich, full, eminent, perfect, joyous, and all that can be deſired condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to true happineſs.</p>
                  <p>Happy then, and thrice happy are they who now in this life covet chiefly, covet on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to have the Lord for their portion,</hi> ſaying, not from the teeth only, but from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:56040:53"/>of their hearts,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.6,</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord himſelf is the portion of mine inheritance, and of my cup: thou ſhalt maintain my lot.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The lot is fallen to me in a fair ground, I have a goodly heritage.</hi> And ſurely he muſt needs be moſt exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantly covetous, that will not be content with ſuch a heritage: and to poſſeſs the Lord himſelf, who poſſeſſeth all things, is <hi>the Riches of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4. PLEASURE.</head>
                  <p>Pleaſure conſiſts in the union of the Soul with an object of Delight: and in Heaven the Soul ſhall be united with the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, and bliſsful object, <hi>viz. The Lord of glory, The light of the World, The God of all Conſolation.</hi> We read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord, is one ſpirit,</hi> which is the height of pleaſure, and perfection of Delight to be ſo intimately joyned to the Lord as to become one ſpirit with him: ſuch do deliciouſly <hi>taſte</hi> and fully <hi>ſee how gracious the Lord is.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no earthly pleaſure like the taſte and ſenſe of the Lord's grace and favour to us: 'Tis yet a greater pleaſure to enjoy the Lord as the only object of Love and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: 'Tis yet more ſweet and pleaſurable to acquieſce and be fully ſatisfied in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the divine Majeſty. But the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of joy is not only to enjoy, but to know that we ſhall ever enjoy the beatifical viſion, and have the fruition of the ſupream beauty, and divine goodneſs for ever and ever.</p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:56040:54"/>
                  <p>Now then,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.4.</note> O my Soul, <hi>Delight thou in the Lord, and he ſhall give thee thy hearts deſire:</hi> In the ſatisfaction and peace of thy deſires does thy happineſs conſiſt, and this is alone in the Lord obtainable:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 89.16,</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed are the people, O Lord, that can rejoyce in thee; they ſhall walk in the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17,"/> — Their delight ſhall be daily in thy name, and in thy righteouſneſs ſhall they make their boaſt:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> For thou art the glory of their ſtrength —</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the ſoul that will rejoyce in God muſt be ſtampt after his Image, and be like unto him, pure as he is pure, holy as he is holy, merciful as he is merciful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 5.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Be ye followers of God as dear children, and walk in love:</hi> and ſo thou may'ſt hope to enjoy the Lord as the ſupream object of love and delight in Heaven.</p>
                  <p>How infinite is the goodneſs, and how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the bounty of the Lord to his good and faithful ſervants, to admit them into the ſame joy, which himſelf enjoys! for ſo ſhall it be ſaid to each of them, <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant — enter thou into the joy of thy Lord,</hi> Matt. 25.25.</p>
                  <p>The joy and felicity of God does conſiſt in the contemplation, and fruition of his own perfections, and felicities: and ſuch is the happineſs of the Saints in Heaven to contemplate, and enjoy the divine Majeſty, in the fulneſs of his joy and pleaſure for evermore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beloved, now we are the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be: but we
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:56040:54"/>know when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him: for we ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi> 1 John 3.2. To ſee God as he is in himſelf clearly, fully, and with fulneſs of ſatisfaction, is the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs both of God himſelf, and of all his Saints in him.</p>
                  <p>O Lord, who haſt prepared for them that love thee ſuch good things as paſs man's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; Pour into our hearts ſuch love towards thee, that we loving thee in and above all things, may obtain thy promiſes which exceed all that we can deſire, through <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. III. <hi>Of the Company of Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1. <hi>Of God's preſence there.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. GOD who is Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, is the chief and principal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant of the Heaven of Heavens: God indeed is every where in reſpect of his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Preſence, Power, but in Heaven in reſpect of his Glory, and the ſupereminent brightneſs of his Majeſty, which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven moſt conſpicuous, full, and raviſhing: nor could Heaven be called ſo, it were not Heaven, if not enlightned, and enhappied by God's ſuperlative preſence there:
<note place="margin">Tho. a Kemp.</note> 
                     <hi>And where ever, O Lord, thou art preſent, either in grace or glory, there is Heaven: and Death and Hell is every where, where thou art abſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:56040:55"/>
                  <p n="2">2. But what doth it avail the company of Heaven that God is there eſpecially preſent, ſince <hi>God dwelleth with the light which no man can approach unto,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> whom no man hath ſeen or can ſee?</hi> The very Angels of Heaven cover their faces with their wings in the preſence of God, that the exceſſive brightneſs of his Majeſty and great Glory overwhelm them not.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.2.</note> 'Tis true, but however ſo much of this eminent glory ſhall appear, and ſo fully the ſplendid Rays thereof be diſplay'd in Heaven, as ſhall raviſh all the bleſſed behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof <hi>with a joy unſpeakable and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſhall be ſatisfied with the plenteouſneſs of thy houſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7. Pſ. 36.8,</note> (<hi>viz.</hi> of Celeſtial glory) <hi>and thou ſhalt give them drink of thy pleaſures as out of a river:</hi> ſo full and overflowing ſhall be their ſatisfaction and contentment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For with thee is the Well of Life,</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> and of all the joys and conſolations of Life: <hi>and in thy light ſhall we ſee light,</hi> even the raviſhing Light of Glory in the Light of God's coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: <hi>in whoſe preſence is fulneſs of joy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2. <hi>The Angels of Heaven.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Next to the bliſsful preſence of God, the ſociety in Heaven is Angels and Archangels, Cherubims and Seraphims, Thrones and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Principalities and Powers, and all the ſeveral Orders of celeſtial Spirits.
<note place="margin">Col. 1.16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The very ſight of one bleſſed Angel upon Earth, would be more joyous and raviſhing than to behold the greateſt beauty, and moſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:56040:55"/>ſplendid excellency that is liable to the eyes of fleſh: yea all the pomp and glory of the World is not comparable to ſuch a ſight: how much more joyful and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will it be, not only to behold, but to enjoy the ſociety of thoſe innumerable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſpirits of whom we read,
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Thouſand thouſands miniſtred unto him, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ten thouſand ſtood before him?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 6.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rev. 21.10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe reſt not day and night, crying, Holy, holy, holy Lord God of Sabbath: Heaven and Earth are full of the Majeſty of thy glory:</hi> To make one in this Hymnidical Quire, and to be received into one of theſe Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Glory from whence the Apoſtate Angels fell, is ſuch an aſtoniſhing joy as cannot by the tongue of men and Angels be expreſſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3. <hi>The Saints in Heaven.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>To theſe Angelical ſpirits are joyned in ſociety as Members of the ſame Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in Heaven, <hi>The glorious company of the Apoſtles, the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, the noble army of Martyrs,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable train of holy Confeſſors, Prieſts, and people of each Sex, and of every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, of whoſe numberleſs number we read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9.
<note place="margin">Rev. 7.9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>And I beheld and lo a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude which no man can number of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and kindreds, and people, and tongues, ſtood before the Throne, and before the Lamb, cloathed with white robes, and palms in their hands—and cryed with a loud voice, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to our God—</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:56040:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe are they, which come out of great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14,"/> and have waſhed their robes in the blood of the Lamb.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore are they before the Throne of God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15,"/> and ſerve him day and night in his Temple, and he that ſitteth upon the Throne ſhall dwell amongſt them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſhall hunger no more,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16,"/> nor thirſt any more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lamb in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed them,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17,"/> and lead them to the living foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of water: And God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bleſſed Souls in whom the King of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry placeth his Throne, and reigneth in them for ever: Bleſſed are thoſe mouths which ſhall taſte and be ſatisfied with the Waters of life everlaſting, and bleſſed are thoſe tears which ſhall be wiped away with the right hand of God himſelf, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting joy ſucceed in the ſtead thereof.</p>
                  <p>Into this glorious Communion of Saints in Heaven, there daily are, and daily ſhall be for ever received all ſuch true ſervants of God, and ſtout Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt, who under his banner have <hi>overcome the Devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked world, all the ſinful luſts of the fleſh:</hi> who have warred a good warfare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe their ghoſtly enemies, and kept the Faith whereinto they were baptized, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any tincture of Hereſie, or Schiſm, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving God's holy Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and walked in the ſame all the days of their life.</p>
                  <p>All of theſe returning from their weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Pilgrimage through the wilderneſs of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:56040:56"/>this world, to their native home of Heaven, ſhall be received into, and rejoyce in their proper and peculiar manſions of peace: each differing indeed in the degrees of <hi>glory,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their difference in the degrees of <hi>grace,</hi> but all ſhall enjoy their full propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of happineſs, and with common joy ſhall ſing together perpetual <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> to him that ſitteth upon the Throne,
<note place="margin">Rev. 5.13.</note> and to the Lamb for ever.</p>
                  <p>And 'tis wonderful amongſt the joys of Heaven, and adds exceedingly to the greatneſs thereof. That as the number of Saints is great, and their joys many: ſo are the joys of each particular Saint, even as many, and bliſsful, as the joys of all: And this becauſe each one ſhall rejoyce as much in the felicity of others, as if 'twere his own peculiar happineſs.</p>
                  <p>Happy and for ever happy were I, if with a floud of Tears and inceſſant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, if with the devour ſurrender of all that I am, and all that I have to the love and ſervice of God, I might be admitted into this celeſtial Society: <hi>To come unto Sion,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22, 23, 24.</note> and unto the City of the living God, the Heavenly Hieruſalem, and to an innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble company of Angels, To the general aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and Church of the firſt-born, which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and to Jeſus the Mediator of the new Covenant</hi>—</p>
                  <p>All this <hi>I believe</hi> as a Chriſtian, but my <hi>Hope</hi> to be admitted into this bleſſed Society
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56040:57"/>is too weakly grounded: whilſt my <hi>Charity</hi> both towards God and his Saints is too cold and benumb'd.</p>
                  <p>I do profeſs to love God, and do deſire that my heart may be every day more and more inflamed with the ſacred fire of divine charity: but doubtleſs I muſt have withal a due regard and veneration for his Saints; for as God is praiſed in his Saints, ſo is he diſhonoured in their diſ-reſpect, <hi>He that toucheth them toucheth the apple of his eye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qui derogat alicui ſanctorum</hi>—Who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts from any of the Saints of God,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 150.1. Zech. 2.8.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts from Chriſt himſelf, who is the Saint of all Saints, and detracts alſo from all the Saints in Heaven; for all are united in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bonds of Charity, all think the ſame thing, all do will alike, and all do love both themſelves and all in one. <hi>T.K.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>c.</hi> 58.</p>
                  <p>If the zeal of ſome perſons towards the Saints in Heaven exceed its due bounds and limits, I muſt not therefore throw off that devout reſpect which is due unto them; remembring that 'tis the end of my <hi>Faith,</hi> the ſumm of my <hi>Hope</hi> to be by holy <hi>Charity</hi> joyned with them in the ſame myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt our common Lord, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and with them to love, and to praiſe the Lord: yea to praiſe and love him for ever,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 84.4.</note> which is the happineſs of the Saints in Heaven: for, <hi>bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe, they will always be praiſing thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And further, the greatneſs of the joys of Heaven may be in ſome degree eſteemed by the greatneſs of their purchace: It is not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56040:57"/>doubted but the bloud of the Son of God is of ſo great value, that the leaſt drop thereof was of ſufficient dignity to redeem ten thouſand worlds; and yet our bleſſed Redeemer, who only knows how to value all things according to their worth, gave every drop of his precious bloud, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with unſpeakable torments, pangs and ſufferings, to purchaſe this Celeſtial in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: hence all truly Religious have Heaven their <hi>deſire,</hi> and the Earth their <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> being of the ſame mind with S. <hi>Paul, Cupio diſſolvi—I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt</hi>—</p>
                  <p>But I am unworthy, too much unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, ſinful duſt and aſhes, to be admitted into the bliſsful preſence of my dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: But I will not deſpair ſince he hath, 1. purchaſed this happineſs for me
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.12, 15, 24.</note>; ſince 2. he hath promiſed to receive me thereinto
<note n="‖" place="margin">Joh. 14.3.</note>; and 3. he hath prayed alſo for my actual poſſeſſion thereof, ſaying, <hi>Father, I will, that they whom thou haſt given me,
<note place="margin">Joh. 17.24.</note> may be with me, where I am, that they may behold the glory which thou haſt given me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Sweeteſt Saviour, who to ſave and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem man vouchſafedſt to be made man, and to appear in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh; O when? when will that happy hour come, wherein I ſhall be admitted to behold thy bleſſed Face,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 17.16.</note> which the Angels in Heaven behold with joy and wonder? <hi>When I ſhall awake up after thy likeneſs, I ſhall be ſatisfied with it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 17.5.</note> ſatisfied to the greateſt height and fulneſs of content, when I ſhall <hi>behold that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:56040:58"/>glory thou hadſt with the Father before the world was:</hi> even ſo come Lord, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> come quickly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. IV. <hi>Of the perpetuity of Heavenly Joys.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE moſt full enjoyment of all the good things this world affords, is not to be called, or accounted <hi>Happineſs,</hi> becauſe they are not only vain and empty of true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, but alſo not permanent and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: <hi>To every purpoſe under the Sun</hi> tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards ſatisfaction and happineſs,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.6.</note> 
                  <hi>there is a time and Judgment,</hi> a <hi>Time</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited for its proſecution and enjoyment, and <hi>Judgment</hi> alſo ſhall paſs upon the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons relating thereunto: it muſt needs follow, <hi>therefore the miſery of man is great upon him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the good things of Heaven are du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, permanent and laſting, hereunto ſhall no Time ſucceed, no Judgment fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               <p>'Tis a maxim in Divinity, <hi>That there is no ſucceſſion in the joys of Heaven,</hi> becauſe what is Eternal admits not of what is firſt, and what is laſt, but is both, and all in the ſame moment, which renders thoſe joys tranſcendently full and raviſhing, ſince in each moment is enjoyed the joys of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:56040:58"/>not increaſing by degrees, or protra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by delays, nor yet augmented by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſpaces of Time, but wholly and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and in the ſame moment is enjoyed and <hi>received</hi> the ſame glory in its height and fulneſs, and this never to be diminiſhed, or decayed, forfeited or loſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Euſ.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Glory</hi> of them that die in <hi>Grace,</hi> is Immortal, their Happineſs Immutable; their Crown immarceſcible; their Life everlaſting; and their Reign with God, and the Lamb for ever and ever. No day does paſs with theſe bleſſed Souls, without its fulneſs of joy and content: This joy ſhall be ever new, and yet ever the ſame: This glory ſhall never wither or decay, but flouriſh for perpetual eternities.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And this muſt needs be ſo; becauſe cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial joy conſiſts as in the bliſsful viſion of God, ſo in an aſſimilation to him: for juſt men made perfect, are immutable in their perfection and felicity by beholding him who is unchangeable: ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>We all as in a Glaſs,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18.</note> beholding the Glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from Glory to Glory even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Moon and the Stars receive their light from the Sun, and become like unto him, by being oppoſite, and in a ſort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Sun's bright face: So the pure Souls in Heaven by ſeeing God who is the Light of lights, are from him enlightened and made like unto him. So ſaith the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Apoſtle: <hi>Beloved,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2.</note> now are we the Sons
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:56040:59"/>of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be: but we know when He ſhall appear, we ſhall be made like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> And that is not as now, <hi>in a glaſs darkly, but face to face</hi> i. e. as fully as our meaſure will contain, our proportion bear, and our degree in Grace require.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gran. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">"The joys of Heaven (ſaith <hi>Gran.</hi>)ſhall continue as many millions of Years as there are Stars in the Firmament, and many more: They ſhall laſt as many hundred millions of years as there have been drops of Rain fallen from Heaven ſince the beginning of the world, and more, much more. In a word, they ſhall endure as long as there is a God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and this God the ſame which was, which is, and which is to come, from everlaſting to everlaſting.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Shall not then my heart be fixed where ſuch laſting joys are to be found? And thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my heart muſt firſt be ſent by way of Harbinger, before my perſon can atrive there: I muſt now have my Converſation in Heaven, before I can have my Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation there: I muſt now be Heavenly minded, or elſe never hope to be admitted into the joys of Heaven.</p>
               <p>But O the heavy burden of my ſins! Theſe do depreſs and weigh down the mind, and make her affections grovel in the duſt: and yet even theſe ſhall not hinder thy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent into Heaven, if thou tread them under thy feet: For every ſin, and vanity trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down, ſubdued and mortified is one
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:56040:59"/>ſtep,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12. <hi>De vitiis noſtris ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, dum vitia cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus.</hi> Luk. 15.7. Heb. 12.1, 2.</note> one Scale or Round of that Celeſtial Ladder, which being ſet upon the Earth reacheth up unto Heaven: which the Angels of Heaven rejoyce to behold.</p>
               <p>And may the right hand of God aſſiſt me, to <hi>lay aſide every weight, and the ſin that doth ſo eaſily beſet me, and to run with patience the race that is ſet before me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Looking unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our Faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him endured the croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the Throne of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed Lord, who haſt made me after thine own Image to attain the perfection and felicity of my Being in the beatifical viſion and fruition of thy Majeſty in Heaven, vouchſafe here to <hi>guide me with thy Counſel, and after that to receive me with glory,</hi> through the Merits and Mediation of thy bleſſed Son and my deareſt Saviour <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt —</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:56040:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> XXIV. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> PARAPHRASED.</head>
               <p>Verſe 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Earth is the Lords and all that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is, the compaſs of the world, and they that dwell therein:</hi> The Heavens are the Lord's chief Dwelling-place, the Earth and all the Nations thereof he hath given to his Son <hi>Jeſus</hi> as he is Redeemer of the World: ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Deſire of me, and I ſhall give thee the heathen for thine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the utmoſt parts of the Earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For he hath founded it upon the ſeas,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and prepared it upon the flouds:</hi> As God hath ſo wiſely ordered the Earth, and the Water, that the one may refreſh, not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow the other: ſo he hath founded his Church upon a Rock above the Flouds of ſecular Cares and Turmoils, and all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing waves of this World's vaſt Sea, which is ſignified by the Situation of his Temple on a Hill: And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> or who ſhall riſe up</hi> (or ſtand) <hi>in his holy place?</hi> Who is he that ſhall be qualified to appear and ſtand in the preſence of God, and to joyn with his people in that ſolemn
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:56040:60"/>worſhip which in his holy Temple is exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited unto him? Such a one is alſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to aſcend and raiſe up his Soul to thoſe mountains of joy in the celeſtial Sion. And ſuch a one is</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that hath clean hands:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The works of whoſe hands are clean from all injuſtice and impurity, and waſhed with the tears of true penitence from the filth of all former pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>And a pure heart,</hi> to all outward, an inward holineſs is required, which conſiſts in the purity of the heart, <hi>viz.</hi> to be pure from all ſordid and vile affections, to be ſincere and without hypocriſie in all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious performances: <hi>that hath not lift up his mind to vanity:</hi> who follows not thoſe pomps and vanities of this wicked world which he once ſo ſolemnly renounced: <hi>nor ſworn to deceive his neighbour,</hi> that will not ſay, much leſs ſwear an untruth, nor yet break his word, eſpecially when confirmed with an oath. Such is the holineſs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence that entitles a people to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God in his Temple upon Earth, and in his Houſe in Heaven, 1. the holineſs of the heart, 2. of the hands, 3. of the tongue; or Holineſs in thought, word, and deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſhall receive the bleſſing from the Lord:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The bleſſings of the Lord ſhall deſcend upon him, when he aſcends into the hill of the Lord: <hi>and righteouſneſs</hi> or mercy in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of his ſins, or the reward of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>i.e.</hi> Salvation not of or from himſelf, or from any but <hi>from the God of his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:56040:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the generation of them that ſeek him:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> theſe are thoſe holy and happy people, who ſo faithfully ſeek the Lord that they find him, <hi>viz.</hi> in grace here, in glory hereafter, which is the double bleſſing <hi>of them that ſeek thy face, O Jacob:</hi> All that be true Iſraelites indeed, thus make their holy and humble addreſſes to the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> for his grace and favour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lift up your heads,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> O ye gates,</hi> or, lift up your gates, O ye Heads or Princes of the Heavenly <hi>Hieruſalem: and be ye lift up ye overlaſting doors</hi> which open the paſſages to life everlaſting: <hi>and the King of glory ſhall come in:</hi> he who hath vanquiſhed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly triumphed over the gates of everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death, over all the ſpirits and powers of darkneſs, is aſcended to open the gates of the Kingdom of Heaven to all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who is the King of glory?</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> in whoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conqueſts we may glory, and in whoſe righteouſneſs we may make our boaſt? <hi>it is the Lord ſtrong and mighty:</hi> who although he ſubmitted himſelf to be betray'd, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, arraigned and condemned to death; yet is he <hi>even the Lord mighty in battle,</hi> who naked and unarmed, hath vanquiſhed by his ſufferings: and by his death overcome death, and him who hath the power of death the Devil: for which victory he rides in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph upon the clouds of Heaven: and therefore,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lift up your Heads, O ye gates</hi> of the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Paradiſe, which have been ſhut againſt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:56040:61"/>the ſons of Men from the fall of the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam: and be ye lift up ye everlaſting doors:</hi> Raiſe up your ſelves ye immortal ſouls, open and be enlarged in your deſires and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto him who hath opened unto you the everlaſting doors of glory: <hi>and the King of glory ſhall come in:</hi> He who is aſcended, will alſo deſcend into you, if pure and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly minded, and thither enwrap and raiſe you whither himſelf is gone before: if yet for your further ſatisfaction you deſire to know
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who is the King of glory:</hi> by whoſe Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant aſcent into Heaven we believe and hope thither to aſcend alſo? It is <hi>even the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> he who hath the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of all the powers of Heaven, Earth, and Hell, who hath the command eſpecially of all the powers and operations, vertues and graces of the Holy Spirit of God, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſeth them accordingly unto all that love and fear his name: <hi>He is the King of glory:</hi> he is glorious indeed above all, and God over all bleſſed for ever: and therefore to him, as is moſt meet, be all glory aſcribed.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:56040:62"/>
               <head>The LXXXIV. <hi>Pſalm</hi> PARAPHRASED.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>O How amiable are thy dwellings,</hi> eſpecially in the high and holy place, <hi>thou Lord of Hoſts,</hi> even of the numerous troops of Angels and Archangels, and of all the powers of Heaven!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My ſoul hath a deſire,</hi> which is more than ordinary,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>'tis <hi>a longing</hi> even to a ſeparation from it ſelf, <hi>to enter into the Courts of the Lord,</hi> to view thoſe ſeveral Manſions of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the bliſsful condition wherein all the Courtiers of the King of Heaven do praiſe him for ever: <hi>my heart and my fleſh</hi> when ſubdued to the ſpirit <hi>rejoyce in the living God;</hi> there's no joy like the joy of his preſence who giveth life, and a heart to pant and breath after the joys of life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſparrow hath found her a houſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and the ſwallow a neſt where to lay her young, even thy Altars:</hi> And O that my Soul could mount as doth the Sparrow upon her wings with inflamed affections after the pleaſures of thy houſe, and that my fleſh might be inſtrumental to my Soul in bringing forth the fruits of the Spirit, to be ſacrific'd upon the Altar of Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto thee, <hi>O Lord of hoſts my King and my God,</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:56040:62"/>whom alone I deſire to adore, worſhip and obey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they</hi> here in hope,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> hereafter in fruition, <hi>who dwell in thy houſe</hi> of Prayer upon Earth, of Praiſe in Heaven, in both <hi>they will always be praiſing thee:</hi> 'Tis our princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal errand to the houſe of God upon earth, and ſhall be our only employment in his houſe of Heaven always to praiſe the Lord.</p>
               <p>But we of thy houſe and family here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, like the young birds near thine Altar are unfledged, and empent in the neſt of this corruptible body which weigheth down the Soul, ſo that amount to Heaven-ward we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without the Divine aſſiſtance; therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſtrength is in thee,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> who derives ſtrength of Grace from thee to praiſe and glorifie thee, and this not only with their mouths, but <hi>in whoſe heart are thy ways,</hi> cordially reſolving and uprightly walking in the ways of thy ſervice, and of their own ſalvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who going through the vale of miſery,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> in their pilgrimage through the miſeries of this ſinful life below, <hi>uſe it for a Well,</hi> even the deep fountain of a broken heart, from whence <hi>the Pools are filled with water,</hi> the eyes flow with tears of that Godly ſorrow which worketh Repentance unto Salvation not to be repented.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They will go from ſtrength to ſtrength,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> from one degree of grace to another, adding to Faith Vertue, to Vertue Knowledge, to Knowledge Temperance, to Temperance
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56040:63"/>Patience, to Patience Godlineſs, to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Brotherly-kindneſs, and to Brotherly-kindneſs Charity, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>unto the God of Gods appeareth every one of them in Sion,</hi> each perſon thus qualified ſhall appear in the preſence of the ſupreme Majeſty of Heaven: which being the felicity whereunto I am cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and earneſtly long for, I therefore humbly beg,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord God of hoſts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> hear my prayer,</hi> thou art the Donor of all thoſe powerfull Graces which mount up our Souls to Heaven; and the Lord of all thoſe hoſts of Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom my Soul longeth to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll'd: <hi>Hearken, O God of Jacob:</hi> aſſiſt me in all my wreſtlings with my ghoſtly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that I may prevail and obtain thy bleſſing, which is to be call'd <hi>Iſrael: Seeing God</hi> the felicity of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> O God, our Defender</hi> againſt all the crafts, and aſſaults of the Devil, the World and the Fleſh: <hi>Look upon the face of thine anointed</hi> our bleſſed Redeemer ſitting on thy right hand, and interceding for us: and may the ſacred beams of his celeſtial light ſhine in our hearts, and appear in the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and righteouſneſs of our lives: that going from ſtrength to ſtrength we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Lord in Sion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For one day in thy Courts</hi> amongſt the Quires of Heaven,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> where the day is but one, as knowing no morrow day, <hi>is better than a thouſand</hi> of the flitting tranſitory days of this mortal life.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:56040:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I had rather be a door-keeper,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> lie at the Threſhhold, ſubmit to the loweſt Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>in the houſe of my God,</hi> the place where his Honour dwelleth who is the God of my Worſhip and Joy, <hi>than to dwell in the tents of ungodlineſs,</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant amongſt the Ungodly of this World, in the moſt ſplendid Condition with all the Delights of the Sons of Men: for 'tis not all the Pomp and Glory, all the Pleaſures and Treaſures of this Life can give any ſolid Satisfaction to the vaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of my immortal Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Lord is a light and defence,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> a light for direction in the way of peace, and a defence for protection, againſt all whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever or whatſoever might diſturb the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and peace of my Soul. <hi>He will give grace and worſhip,</hi> Grace to ſerve him truly here, and Worſhip or Glory to crown our ſervices hereafter: <hi>and no good thing will he withhold from them that lead a godly life:</hi> who truly love and fear God, and wait for his promiſes in the obedience of his precepts, ſhall enjoy all that is truly good, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to their Eternal happineſs in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord God of Hoſts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> bleſſed is the man that putteth his truſt in thee:</hi> not roving in his hopes and deſires after the exterior, empty, tranſitory Conſolations of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but among the ſundry and manifold Changes of the World hath his heart ſurely fixed there, where true joys are to be found, which is alone in the Preſence of the God
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:56040:64"/>of Heaven: where all do rejoyce together and ſing for ever.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>AS an Earneſt of this Everlaſting Joy and Felicity, <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> 
                  <hi>One thing have I deſired of the Lord, which I will require: even that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the days of my life, to behold the fair beauty of the Lord, and to viſit his Temple.</hi> Amen.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:56040:64"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF the Four laſt things in general.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the ſhortneſs and frailty of this preſent Life.</hi> 5</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſtine<hi>'s Meditation on this ſubject.</hi> 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the frequent remembrance of Death.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Horror of Death.</hi> 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the uncertainty of Death, and preparation for it.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 39 <hi>Pſalm illuſtrated with notes.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 90 <hi>Pſalm illuſtrated with notes.</hi> 33</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The II. general Head.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF Judgment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of particular Judgment.</hi> 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the general Judgment.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 26 <hi>Pſalm paraphraſed.</hi> 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 43 <hi>Pſalm paraphraſed.</hi> 58</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The III. general Head.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF the pains of Hell.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the pain of Loſs.</hi> 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the darkneſs of Hell.</hi> 65</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the fire of Hell.</hi> 67</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:56040:65"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the extent of Hell-pains.</hi> 71</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the bonds and chains of Hell.</hi> 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Laments of Hell.</hi> 78</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the perpetuity of Hell-torments.</hi> 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 86 <hi>Pſalm paraphraſed.</hi> 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 88 <hi>Pſalm paraphraſed.</hi> 88</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The IV. general Head.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF Heaven.</hi> 93</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the place call'd Heaven,</hi> 1. <hi>Its greatneſs,</hi> 97 2. <hi>Its brightneſs and ſplendor,</hi> 98 3. <hi>Its tranquility and peace,</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the good things of Heaven,</hi> 1. <hi>Honour,</hi> 100 2. <hi>Power,</hi> 101 3. <hi>Riches,</hi> 102 4. <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Company of Heaven,</hi> 1. <hi>God's preſence there,</hi> 105 2. <hi>Of the Angels of Heaven,</hi> 106 3. <hi>Of the Saints in Heaven.</hi> 107</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the perpetuity of heavenly Joys.</hi> 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 24 <hi>Pſalm paraphraſed.</hi> 116</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 84 <hi>Pſalm paraphraſed.</hi> 120</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56040:65"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for and Sold by <hi>Luke Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redith,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <div n="Jeremy Taylor" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Books written by</hi> Jer. Taylor, <hi>D. D. and late Lord Biſhop of</hi> Down <hi>and</hi> Connor.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ctor Dubitantium:</hi> or, The Rule of Conſcience, in Five Books in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Great Exemplar;</hi> or, The Life and Death of the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in <hi>Folio,</hi> with Figures ſuitable to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Story, ingrav'd in Copper: whereunto are added the Lives and Martyrdoms of the Apoſtle. By <hi>W. Cave,</hi> D. D.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; or, A Collection of Polemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſcourſes addreſſed againſt the Enemies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> in large <hi>Folio,</hi> the Third Edition.</p>
               <p>The Rules and Exerciſes of Holy Living and Dying The Fifteenth Edition, newly Printed, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Collection of Sermons, <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Golden Grove; A Choice Manual, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is to be believed, practiſed, and deſired or prayed for: the Prayers being fitted to the ſeveral Days of the Week; alſo Feſtival Hymns according to the manner of the Ancient Church.</p>
               <p>The Pſalter of <hi>David,</hi> with Titles and Collects according to the Matter of each Pſalm; whereunto are added Devotions for the Help and Aſſiſtance of all Chriſtian People in all Occaſions and Neceſſities. The Tenth Edition: in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56040:66"/>
               <p>A Collection of Offices, or Forms of Prayers in Caſes <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary;</hi> taken out of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and the ancient <hi>Liturgies</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Churches,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Greek:</hi> Together with a large <hi>Preface</hi> in Vindication of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> The Second Edition, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Simon Patrick" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Books written by the Reverend Dr.</hi> Patrick, <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Ely.</head>
               <p>THE Chriſtian's Sacrifice: A Treatiſe, ſhewing the Neceſſity, End, and Manner of receiving the Holy Communion; together with ſuitable Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Meditations for every Month in the Year; and the principal Feſtivals in Memory of our Bleſſed Saviour. In Four Parts. The Third Edition cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
               <p>The Devout Chriſtian inſtructed how to pray and give Thanks to God: Or, A Book of Devotions for Families, and particular Perſons, in moſt of the Concerns of Humane Life. The Eighth Edition, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Advice to a Friend. The Fourth Edition, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> Paraphraſed, in <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo.</hi> Newly printed in one Volume.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> Paraphras'd, with Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to each Chapter, which ſupply the place of Commenting.</p>
               <p>A Paraphraſe upon the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> and the <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> with Arguments to each other Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Annotations thereupon: in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Truth of Chriſtian Religion, in Six Books: written in Latin by <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and now Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with the Addition of a Seventh Book againſt the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Catalogue.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56040:66"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
